<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ansvver to a passage in Mr. Baxter's book, intituled, A key for Catholicks, beginning pag. 321, concerning the King's being put to death by John Nanfan, Esq.</title>
            <author>Nanfan, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52586</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N148</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3575</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12083783</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12083783</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53682</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52586)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53682)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 818:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ansvver to a passage in Mr. Baxter's book, intituled, A key for Catholicks, beginning pag. 321, concerning the King's being put to death by John Nanfan, Esq.</title>
                  <author>Nanfan, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 73 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Jones ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691. --  Key for Catholicks.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53682:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSVVER TO A PASSAGE IN Mr. Baxters Book, INTITULED, <hi>A Key for Catholicks:</hi> Beginning <hi>pag.</hi> 321. concerning the KING'S being put to Death.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Nanfan <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Jones</hi> Book-Seller in <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:53682:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53682:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>I Know not why I ſhould endeavour to pleaſe or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy concerning this, that I throw it abroad, which was ſolitary, and private to me in the worſt of times, or any ſuch Apologies, or endeavours, or eſſayes, to take off cenſure. It were too much ſubmitting, and ſubjecting to others; let the matter and ſubject it ſelf ſpeak for it, and let others condeſcend their Judgments to it, and that is all that is deſired: It has no end out of it ſelf. Particular Reaſons I have; as that there is as good warrant in me to take off Mr. <hi>Baxter's</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptive, violent, injurious Arguments againſt Kings, and Governments, as he to aſſert them; the cauſe is his: he the aſſailant, I am but the Defendant: The ſally out into the World, and into ſo great an Intereſt as Kings Governments, and terms of ſubmiſſion to them, and when in ſome caſes, the people to kill, and ſlay, and deſtroy all; theſe great exorbitant, monſtrous conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons come from Mr. <hi>Baxter:</hi> he hath ſtated caſes, fixed them to Poſterity, that they may be fruitfull to generate in the World; mine but an Arrest upon him, both to redeem truth, and likewiſe to let the World know that
<pb facs="tcp:53682:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
great Writers may contain much iniquity in them, and how the World is to beware of them.</p>
            <p>But why do I entertain the Reader at the Porch, or without the Door, and ſeem to intreat him to like the ſtructure within, which he is to behold? Therefore I give it off, only this, that it ſpeaks that time, that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate condition then it was made to: and making it now another thing, is not my end, but to ſhew and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the ſame; for every thing has its rectitude in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the point it tends to.</p>
            <p>And this good in it, that though the ſubject ſad, yet it raiſes more conſiderations out of it, and from it; for we have our enjoyment from good times, but our infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation more from bad: And beſides, theſe conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are general, ſo as no time o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> them; truths that are not particular in their nature, have an eternity in them. And for ought we know, there is as great a Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome required to retain our Government as to attain to it: that lay but in one deſign, and eaſily done, becauſe not diſcerned in the doing; this is of a perpetual provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and perpetual danger, and enmity againſt it, and we are to betake our ſelves to all conſiderations where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our good and evill is contained: and publick good is the great end, the wheel, and ſway, and compaſs to all motions, all particulars but conſidered in it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53682:3"/>
            <head>AN ANSVVER TO A PASSAGE IN Mr. <hi>BAXTERS</hi> Book; INTITULED, A Key for Catholicks; <hi>Beginning,</hi> pag. 321. <hi>concerning the Kings being put to Death.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HE begins thus, <hi>Concerning the Death of the King, I ſhall not meddle at this time with the cauſe, nor meddle with the Reaſons brought for it, or againſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It will appear, by ſo much as concerns me to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to, whether Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> meddle with the Cauſe or not. This pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended abſtemiouſneſs, is but to make it pierce the deeper, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53682:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſtrength more conſiderable: He is as great an Aſſertor of it, as poſſibly he can find matter to make it ſpeculatively true, though in fact he keeps out of it.</p>
            <p>Whilſt he vies Intereſts with the Papiſts, he takes upon him to hold the Ballance; this of murdering the King, in manner and form of it, in one end of the Scale; and that of the Popes curſing Kings, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently murdering of them, in the other: and he finds his leighter by much, which is the triumph of his cauſe; and to this he does abet all his ſtrength to make it good, which is by making the evil of it leſs; ſo as this is the very ſtate of his Cauſe, and you ſhall ſee him appearing in it by degrees, like a winding ſtairs, till he comes up to the top. I ſhall take all his by way of Objections, and anſwer to it.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>The Providence of God hath ſo contrived it, that nothing but igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or blind malice, can lay it upon the Proteſtants, Epiſcopal, or Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, that strove ſo much against it, and ſuffered ſo much for it as they have done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In this he doth confound Intereſts, to joyn the Epiſcopal with the Presbyterian; I am very confident the Epiſcopal would not mix with any other Intereſt in ſuch a defence; and to peece them to the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, is an abuſe. It is a kind of Policy to defend a corrupt cauſe, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king into it that which cannot be denyed to be juſt, and clear in it ſelf, and under colour of that to cry up the whole.</p>
            <p>Not that I mean to condemn the Presbyterians directly for the Kings Death; I leave that to particular Arguments as they fall out, and to be underſtood in a juſt medium in it, relating to Presbyterians and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants both, that acted. But his further,</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>When many on the other ſide charged the</hi> Scots, <hi>and the Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Ministers of</hi> London, <hi>with thoſe that were put to death, for going too far on the other ſide, in manifesting their distasts; of which I take not on me to be Judg, but mention it onely as Evidence that clears them from the Deed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> How cautious Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> is, that he will not take upon him to be Judg, who were in the right of thoſe two parties, one the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians that diſliked the putting the King to Death, and the other that act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, and were angry with them for diſliking, and expreſſing their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes. He is very wary in this here, with his reſerves and ſavings, that he does declare it only as matter of fact; ſo tender is he not to engage too far, to judg or conclude any thing in it. This makes me doubt, that in ſome paſſages hereafter, where he calls it odious, and deteſtable, that he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53682:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
has a latitude in thoſe expreſſions; for an Act may have thoſe epithite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and yet poſſibly be lawful: Now whether there may not be ſome thing of this in it, though he declares againſt the fact; I may doubt, becauſe of his denying here to condemn it. Certainly, he that in his Soul has not a full abhorrency to it, is of the infection of it; and no other conſtruction can be made. He goes on,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> To vindicate the Proteſtants openly before all the World, and to all poſterity from that fact, it is moſt publickly known, that both Houſes of <hi>Parliament,</hi> in their proteſtations engaged themſelves and the Nation to be true to the <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This was but in order to the War, which they were forming againſt the <hi>King;</hi> It was made the very means of raiſing the People by whom the War muſt be acted. Upon a plain down-right way of fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the <hi>King</hi> could have had no colour with the People; who are always in ſuch popular confuſions to be deceived and abuſed, to ſerve to others ends.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> That they openly profeſſed to manage their War for <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament;</hi> not againſt his Perſon and Authority, but againſt Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents that were fled from Juſtice, and againſt evil Councellers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> would make their War juſt, That it was profeſſed and engaged to be managed for <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament;</hi> Certainly, they did no more in this then all Subjects ever did that made War againſt their <hi>King,</hi> that is, to diſſtinguiſh the <hi>King</hi>'s intereſt from the cauſe of the War: A leſs pretenſion cannot be for a Rebellion; Rebellion in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it, is ſo much a Monſter, as it ſeeks the beſt cover, and never has the face to pretend againſt the <hi>King.</hi> The fallaciouſneſſe of this, he himſelf evinced in his following, by ſaying, or at leaſt concluding, <hi>That a ſubdued King is never fit again to rule over the People that ſubdued him:</hi> We need no other evidence now then the things themſelves, ſo as we are to argue <hi>à poſteriori,</hi> from the ends and iſſues, back to their cauſes; that is, that all War taken up by Subjects upon any pretence whatſoever, or by whatſoever caution, or limitation evermore, in the nature of it, intends the deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> That the two Nations of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> did in the midſt of the Wars, ſwear in the Solemn League and Covenant, to be true to the King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Still this was but the ſame thing to ſtrengthen the confederacy; when at any time there ſhould be a fainting or ſcrupling by the People, a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53682:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
new engagement, or profeſſion to publick ends, and to common preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, whereof the <hi>King</hi> was the Head, would give new life to it. And this was all the uſe that ever was made of that Covenant; It never ſerved the <hi>King</hi> at all, but to beat him down and deſtroy him.</p>
            <p>And all bringing the people into a body by Covenant, is unlawful; becauſe Government meerly conſiſts in having no contracts of the people acting of themſelves.</p>
            <p>And likewiſe the Covenant was not abſolute, as a Kings preſervation ſhould be, but had a looſe in it, that made it nothing; It was with a ſo far, as conſiſts with Religion, Laws, and Liberties: The King's life, and his Rights were not abſolutely covenanted; O God forbid, there ſhould not be an exception, as to Religion, Laws, and Liberties! and this a deſtroying power would be interpreter of. So as this Covenant was like <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s Image; the upper parts of Gold and Silver, the lower parts of Iron, and baſer ſtuff; but the truth is, when men Covenant things contradictory, as to fight againſt the King, and to be true to him; they cannot be expected to perform better: for truth is of that Nature, that though men abuſe it ever ſo much, yet it is unalterable: Effects are certain to their cauſes, and own their true Parents.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> The Committees, Commanders, Miniſters and People, thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Land; profeſſed openly to go only upon ſuch tearms as managing but a defenſive War againſt the King's miſcariages, but an offenſive againſt delinquent Subjects.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is no ſuch thing in Nature, as a defenſive War againſt a King, by Subjects; as I ſhall more clearly demonſtrate in due place. But in this Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> grants, as far as is poſſible, to make it defenſive, neceſſary, and of meer neceſſity on the King's part: It was offenſive againſt delinquent Subjects, as much as to ſay, it was a War on the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments part, to the deſtruction of the King's Subjects, and the King muſt be unconcern'd in it, ſit by and be idle; with-draw all protection, and become immediately out of poſſeſſion. For ſuch is the Nature, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a King, when an armed power is acting, and the King ſedentary, and not reſiſting.</p>
            <p>In a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> a War cannot be againſt any party, and not againſt the <hi>King;</hi> for it deprives the <hi>King,</hi> of his governing power.</p>
            <p>Conſider but what the Nature of a War taken up by the People is (for his Senate ſignifies nothing, he ſhall find the whole is but King and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple); Firſt, when it once becomes powerful, it gains from its very unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53682:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
a liberty to be governed by none; for in unlawful actions they are all equals. No obligation can ariſe but where there is a primary juſtice to fix it to, and we ſee in this, every thing that prevails never diſputes right; and the reaſon is, becauſe the whole is unlawful. And I preſent this to Mr. <hi>Baxter's</hi> reaſon, as it is viſible to his obſervation, to ſhew him that ſuch a kind of War can be wicked, but cannot find a Juſtice to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern it; and his firſt of rebelling with caution, and condition, was a meer fiction. His next is a Narrative only.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>In that it was known that the Army was quite altered, not only by a new modelling, but by an inteſtine Jeſuitical corrupting of multitudes of Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, before this odious Fact could be done. And it was known, that the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted part of the Army, though the fewer, did ſo excel the reſt in Induſtry and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, that thereby they hindred their Oppoſition: And it is known that the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuited party, that afterwards ſo many of them turned</hi> Levellers, <hi>did draw unto them the</hi> Anabaptiſts, Libertines, <hi>and other Sects, upon a Conjunction of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, and by many ſly pretences, eſpecially tying all together by the predicated Liberty for all Religions. And yet after this, the World knows they were fain, before they could accompliſh it, to maſter the City of</hi> London, <hi>to maſter the Parliament, to impriſon and caſt out the Members, and to retain but a few that were partly of their mind, and partly ſeduced or over-awed by them, to joyn with them in the work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is incident alwayes that when a King's Power is diſſolved, all Wickedneſs, and all manner of Factions and Diviſions, do grow up in the place of it; for want of that Power to retain them, and their own guilt ſtill driving them on, and being all equals in wickedneſs; theſe are ſo natural Cauſes as I wonder any one can diſpute them: They ly all in the firſt Cauſe of taking away the King's Power, all the reſt reſults out of it.</p>
            <p>And they themſelvs had proceeded ſo far, as to all Deprivations of the King, and all manner of Imputations and Proſcriptions, as guilty of all the evill of the War; ſetling him in the condition of a Traytor, being King, kept him in cuſtody after they had bought him of the <hi>Scots,</hi> and not enduring him to terms till the laſt, when it was too late.</p>
            <p>I grant, his party would not have had the King bin killed; A poor reſerve! when he is made incapable of any other condition. If the People did but know what it were to ſubdue their King, and deprive him of his Power, they would never diſpute terms of diſpoſing him: It is the ſame thing as killing, it ſtays but the acting: And this ſervs to all he ſays of this kind.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:53682:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>And let me inſert this, though I conſent wholly to his Narrative; that it is very ordinary and natural, when a party acts in a joynt wickedneſs and cruelty, and after grow into difference; the leſs able party will ever diſlike what the other go thorow with to act, and pretend to a greater Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Moderation, when it is acted by others, and out of their Power: but more of this in the following.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>It is known, that before they were put out and impriſoned by the Army, the Commons voted the King's Conceſſions in the Treaty, to be ſo far ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory, as that they would have proceeded on them, towards a full agreement. See Mr.</hi> Prin's <hi>large Speech in the houſe to that end: And if they had not ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly been ſecluded and impriſoned, they had agreed with the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This was when they had no other Intereſt left them but that of the King's, which they had laid by, and trampled upon perpetually, till now they muſt loſe all unleſs they held by that: How endleſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiate were they in exerciſing their own greatneſs upon the King's weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; the People perpetually defrauded of the Accommodation by them thirſted after: Never any thing ſatisfactory, though they had all; and play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with this their own fortune, and moſt delectable greatneſs too long, at length (as all new exceſſive things are incident to change) the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents by him mentioned fell in amongſt themſelves; and they were vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting concluſions with the King, juſt the inſtant before they brake. Some ſecluded, ſome made Priſoners; ſome, to avoid worſe, fled out of the Land.</p>
            <p>It is the miſ-fortune and condition of Tyrants to be ſubject to their own Power, and Slaves to it. An Army eſpecially, that ſervs but to Subjects againſt their Soveraign, will, though humble, and obedient at firſt, as all ſuch things are, grow inſolent; as to equals, treat conditions, and have other Intereſts. It is like a hand-Wolf, that though he will be played with for a time, yet his Keepers and Maſters are Subject to be torn in pieces by him upon the change of his humour. Such was this their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, a hand-Wolf too long played with, till it grew to know its own ſtrength, and to conſider that all Rights were alike againſt the King, and amongſt the People.</p>
            <p>And then for the Nature of the Agreement with the King, It was that for ſome time, he ſhould have been without his Power; and all agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with a King that veſt him not in his Power, are nothing at all in conſideration to a King, for a future reſtoring, or for ſecurity againſt the preſent Power; they are things that cannot be, and any intervening time
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53682:6"/>
would have raiſed new accidents from ſo great an impending cauſe; the greateſt in the World, beyond and above all conditions, and not being, can have no aſſurance of future being.</p>
            <p>I call to mind a Paſſage in a Book called <hi>A Plea for Parliaments,</hi> ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be written by Sir <hi>Walter Rawley,</hi> that it was moved in Parliament in Queen <hi>Maryes</hi> time, that if ſhe ſhould dy, leaving Iſſue; King <hi>Philip</hi> the Father, and now Matrimonial King, ſhould hold the Kingdom till the Iſſue came of Age to govern, and ſtrong bonds ſhould be given for the Surrender. And a certain Lord (none of the wiſeſt, ſaith the ſtory) who had ſate ſilent during the whole Debate, at laſt boulted out this Queſtion; <hi>Who ſhould ſue thoſe bonds againſt the King?</hi> They were all preſently ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and ſo it fell, not a word more of it: As much as to ſay, An abſolute Power in poſſeſſion is above all Condition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> One thing I ſhall call him back to, that is, ſaying, That <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes who are now firm and loyall to the preſent Power, ſuppoſing it to be ſet over us by God, and therefore would abhor the like practices againſt them, do yet deteſt that Fact that intervened, and made way to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I would deſire to be ſatisfied, how Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> can reconcile his Divinity. This Power ſet over us by God, therefore not to act againſt it: The King's Power either not in his ſenſe ſet over us by God, or elſe why did he act againſt it? If he ſay, to reform it; then, why not this? Are all things ſo ſatisfactory to him in this as needs no Reformation? The other Power of the King's, peradventure in his ſenſe, was not ſet over us by God. But how this is, I would deſire him to diſtinguiſh, and when and where he would make a ſtop to man's acting: I ſhould be very glad that the World were ſatisfied with it, that Supream Power ſhould be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable; I would truſt God and Man, and humane caſual events, with my ſhare out of it, becauſe I ſee pretended Reformations never coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervail the miſchief of Rebellions.</p>
            <p>But in the mean time, I deſire him to diſtinguiſh betwixt theſe two Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, why he is indulgent to this now; and ſo much an Actor and Engineer imploying his Divinity, Learning, and Paſſion, againſt the old. Let me ſtill hold him to this his own ground, <hi>Set over us by God:</hi> Whether he means of God's general Providence as the great Governour of the World, and ſo aſſigning Governours ſubordinate, or elſe that he means it in ſpecial to this, out of his fancy, or favour to it: I would have him diſtinguiſh, and I am prepared for him with a further inquiry. But in the mean time, becauſe I know not my future opportunities, I ſhall further trouble him,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53682:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
I ſuppoſe he will not otherwiſe call or account it <hi>Set over us by God,</hi> then as all other wicked things come to paſs; as this did, through the blood and death of the King, which intervening cauſe he denotes deteſtable. Now what obligation extraordinary, and which the former Government did not, this throws upon man, is my Inquiry? Where ſhall man's Wiſdom act or reſt? This done by man, and why may not man undo his own Work? Is there a Fate upon him in one Action more than in another, if Reaſon doth nor ſtate a difference? Is his Divinity otherwiſe intelligible to him than by his Reaſon? Does he act freely in ſome things, and not in all? Are ſome things of God, and not all things? If he will ſay, the being of Kings and Supream Governours ſhould oblige an unqueſtionable Obedience, let him anſwer then for deſtroying the former: Is a leſs At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute due to a rightful King than to his Deſtroyer? His intended Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation by a War, intended no leſs than deſtroying his Power to reſiſt. Beſides, it will be very hard for him, even in his own ſenſe, to determine betwixt a true King driven or kept out, and a King in Fact, and by Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation and King-killing, which ſhould draw to it the Right and Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Conſcience: and likewiſe hard for him to reſolve, when the new is ſo ſettled, the other in being though out of poſſeſſing, as to make Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence entire. Therefore ſurely it were beſt God were left out, who in theſe our miſerable times hath been made a Stale and a Colour for all the cruelties men have committed: Certainly Divinity, in underſtanding the Will of God, admits of ſome diſtinction betwixt things done to God's Glory, and the worſt of Man's Actions, though all alike under the common Providence of God: But a little further, I deſire his Patience to go along with me. A King killed to day, and the Regicide by his party becomes King in Fact, and in Power to morrow; then to morrow he obeys him with all Attributes of God's greatneſs, Will, Power, Goodneſs; and if him, another on the next day, then him too, and ſo on ſtill. It is known, that after it began in <hi>Nero,</hi> how many Emperors came upon the ſtage of the World in a ſhort ſpace; killing and diſpatching the preſent, gave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the latter. Now, where will he define or place his Providence, or bound Man's acting? Certainly, if at all, in the firſt place, for many reaſons; as the firſt looſe or progreſſion to Wickedneſs is the true cauſe of all the following; and becauſe there is a natural ſtay in the firſt, which looſed, the like is not found in the following. The truth is, it is a fooliſh thing to ty up Man's reaſon more in one thing than in another; for if he argues things greater or higher to him, he argues ſtill but to his reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:53682:7"/>In the next he goes higher, and like a Stone falling, the nearer the Center, the greater its force; ſo he, as he proceeds farther, grows fiercer about the King's being judged to death by his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and he extenuates the Fact by the formality of it: I ſhould wrong him not to give it him in his own words.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>I muſt needs add, that every wiſe man ſees that the caſe it ſelf much differs from the</hi> Papiſts. <hi>If the Body of a Common-wealth, or thoſe that have part in the Legiſlative Power, and ſo in the Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſhould unwillingly be engaged in a War with the Prince, and after many years blood and deſolations, judicially take away his life as guilty of all this Blood, and not to be truſted any more with Government: And all this do, not as private men, but as the remaining Soveraign Power, and ſay, they do it according to Laws: undoubtedly this caſe doth very much differ from the Powder-Plot, or Papiſts murdering of Kings, and teaching that it is lawfull for a private hand to do it, if he be but an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, or but depoſed, yea, or excommunicated by the Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Mine thorow-out will give a larger conſideration upon the whole; But to his particulars, as they paſs from him.</p>
            <p>Firſt he ſaith, <hi>have part in the Legiſlative Power, and ſo in the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy,</hi> wherein he confounds them both together, and makes it but one and the ſame. To <hi>have part in the Legiſlative Power,</hi> as to the altering of Laws, or any other thing wherein it is exerciſed, implies a right in the People as to thoſe things, and in the Nature of it a Negative Right: That is, that it could not be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their conſents; and this Negative Right gives them not a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Right.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> His next is, and <hi>judicially take away his life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The King's own words, at that hard time with him, when they ſate over him as his Judges, are moſt worthy as from himſelf to be remembred; He told them how far his caſe was, their King, from being judged by them, when as all judicature was derived from him to them. And certainly, this alone of the King's carryes Argument enough in it againſt all judging or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning of King's or Supreams; for no Power can create a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er againſt it ſelf, and nothing in nature can go higher than its firſt Cauſe: A Power derived out of the King, cannot be underſtood to be againſt the King. He goes on to criminate the King, whether his ſenſe or ſuppoſition I know not.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:53682:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Object. <hi>As guilty of all that Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The King's unhappineſs was, to be made guilty becauſe he was not able to defend himſelf: And ſo ſhall every <hi>Prince</hi> be that is overcome by his Subjects, they muſt be guilty to be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Tyrants Wickedneſs do but prepare a guilt for the cruelties they mean to act; It was the <hi>Kings</hi> own ſaying, That he had not one foot of Land in his own <hi>Kingdom,</hi> but what his Army ſtood up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It was not poſſible to be a more neceſſitated War than the <hi>King</hi>'s, for all the World knows, it was deſtiny upon him; never perſons ſo obdurate as to take no conditions, never could find any <hi>Medium</hi> betwixt deſtroying their Soveraign, and their own deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateneſs. And the <hi>King</hi>'s Intereſt wholly defenſive, not only for himſelf but for his <hi>Kingdoms;</hi> and that made him ſay upon his death, which ſeals all truths, that he dyed his Kingdom's and his People's Martyr. It were eaſy to go upon demonſtrative proofs in this, but it would involve the whole Cauſe, which we are to take in its parts.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>And not any more to be truſted with Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is the reaſon in the Eye of the Law, which ſees to the end in the firſt act, that all attempts to bring a <hi>King</hi> under any Power of his People, are the ſame as to deſtroy him; And this was reſolved in the Caſe of the Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> he would ſeize upon the Court,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Camden's</hi> Annals, <hi>p.</hi> 547, 548.</note> take the Queen into his Power, not otherwiſe harm her; remove from her evil Counſellors, but honour her Perſon.</p>
            <p>Now this was all adjudged high Treaſon in every circumſtance of it, becauſe all depriving of a Soveraign <hi>Prince</hi> of his Power is the ſame as to deſtroy him. <hi>Eſſex</hi> himſelf ſaid before his death, that the <hi>Queen</hi> and he both could not live; and others, the moſt eminent of his party, acknowledged that though it were not their deſign to deſtroy the <hi>Queen,</hi> yet it would have been the neceſſity of their proceeding, if they had prevailed; ſo as the effects of Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Mr. <hi>Baxte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> makes his Arguments. Before I put an end to theſe Papers I ſhall reſume again his words, <hi>[No more to be truſted with Government,]</hi> to make inquiry into the Rights of <hi>Kings,</hi> and their Original; to find their firſt Cauſe, and to judge of their extent and terminations. But at preſent to his next.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>And all this they do</hi> (that is, take away the King's life), <hi>not as private men, but the remaining Soveraign Power, and ſay, they do it according to Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:53682:8"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Objective words, without any proving, brings every thing to a queſtion; as this hath two very great falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods and high preſumptions in it: The one, a Soveraignty in the <hi>Parliament;</hi> the other, a lawfulneſs of killing the King. For the firſt, which is made the conveyance to the latter to erect ſo high a wickedneſs upon, a Parliamentary Supremacy, to make them an expedient to kill their <hi>King,</hi> is no more true, than that there were two <hi>Kings</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> two Suns in the Firmament of Government, two Centers in a Circle, two Infinites, or any Impoſſibility that can be imagined. But I ſhall have occaſion to treat the Argument of the <hi>King</hi>'s ſole Soveraignty in divers paſſages; onely at preſent to it, the <hi>Parliament</hi> is but a borrowed light, all derived out of the <hi>King,</hi> the Fountain; in oppoſition to the <hi>King</hi> it is but an opacous Body, the light withdrawn from it. <hi>Grotius</hi> ſtates the caſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Grotius</hi> de jure Villi, <hi>54.</hi> inventi ſunt noſtro ſeculo.</note> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Subordinates may act againſt the Supream Power; that is, whether any ſort of Magiſtracy under a <hi>King</hi> have any quality or conſideration in them, as dividing from the <hi>King;</hi> and he reſolves it in the Negative: He reaſons it thus, that theſe publick Perſons are but private in reſpect of the chief, and all the faculty of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in them is ſo ſubjected to the chief Power, as whatſoever they act againſt the Will of that is defective of the faculty, and is but of the Nature of a private Act. I ſhall give it off here, becauſe hereafter I ſhall demonſtrate the impoſſibility of two Soveraignties or Supremacies in one Government, and reduce <hi>Parliamentary</hi> Rights to their due Qualification.</p>
            <p>Now then, take away this, the other falls; this the Theatre Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> erects for judging the <hi>King,</hi> and Scaffold for beheading him. The truth is, the Laws are all ſilent about this Queſtion, Whether a <hi>Parliament</hi> may commit Tteaſon: ſo as if we ſhall not take them in their general underſtanding we have no law in this Caſe.</p>
            <p>It is a thing not to be doubted, that the Law never had it in ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, that there was any exception to the committing of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; ſo as no ſuch thing mentioned in Laws, nor ever entred into the mind of any Commentator, who write at large, and many times their own conceipts; yet it never came into the conceipt of any Perſon, to except a <hi>Parliament</hi> for committing Treaſon. It is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times in Nature the ſtrongeſt Law that which is not mentioned;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53682:9"/>
becauſe the caſe never imagined to be, and therefore not provided for.</p>
            <p>So as if Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> will not take all the Laws that are generall, without exception, to include all Perſons, then is the <hi>King</hi> without Law, as againſt a <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the ſenſe of the Laws reſpect the <hi>King</hi> without any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Perſons, no ſenſe or intendment of that, but only the end to which it is directed; and therefore it is called <hi>Crimen laeſae Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtatis;</hi> which ſhews where the end is, in the King's Preſervation, but the means never differenced in reſpect of any.</p>
            <p>It were in vain to enumerate the Laws, and to aggravate them; all dread, and all ſaving, being to the life of the Government, the <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This differencing is out of all Laws, never thought of; it had its Law and Execution at once, as Treaſons are never owned till they are acted.</p>
            <p>But let the Reader conſider upon the Statute 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. which is the Declarative of Treaſons, whether there is diſcernable any differencing in it, or exceptions of Perſons, or Callings, or of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, or any imagination of this Propoſition, till now that wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſtrives to defend it ſelf.</p>
            <p>I ſhall take occaſion here to ſpeak to former actings of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> upon <hi>Kings,</hi> depoſing them, and conſequently killing them; becauſe the Nature of man is, to think any thing that hath bin done may be done, and ſo never finds end of wickedneſs but to make it infinite. Any extraordinary or tranſcendent acting upon Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though never ſo unlawful and violent, yet if it become pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful, it commonly creates ſomething to others to derive from it; as thoſe Perſons, whom Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> would vindicate, long before they divided, declared, That in caſe they ſhould act to the higheſt Preſidents, they ſhould not fail in duty or truſt; having their eye and aim upon the depoſing of <hi>Kings, Ed.</hi> 2. &amp; <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. And the laſt Actors that compleated the Tragedy, conclude power of <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments</hi> from former deſtroying <hi>Kings,</hi> and ſetting up others.</p>
            <p>I ſhall produce it only into ſome conſiderations by Epitome on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, leaving the large Subject of it to the Hiſtories, how thoſe <hi>Princes</hi> came to be declined, and loſe their Power. The firſt, <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. his condition was, to be Priſoner to his own <hi>Queen,</hi> and his Son,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53682:9"/>
a <hi>Prince</hi> of fourteen years of Age; and the implacable hatred of the <hi>Queen</hi> and her party was ſuch, as the <hi>King</hi> muſt be deſtroyed; no competition being to them both: The whole Power was with them; they call a <hi>Parliament,</hi> which acted meerly as they preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. The <hi>King,</hi> depoſed by Act of <hi>Parliament,</hi> ſubmitted, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, in hope of life, which he could not have. The other as unhappy, <hi>Richard</hi> II. Priſoner to the Uſurper <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> his Couſin-Germane. The Fate of ſubdued <hi>Kings</hi> by Traytors, is ever to run into the ſame Center; Traytors leave nothing undone of the laſt Act of deſtroying. Now, the actings being thus, what are the conſiderations upon it; Firſt, theſe Perſons, and the <hi>Parliament,</hi> were the firſt that ever acted ſo in <hi>England,</hi> and ſo muſt derive the Juſtice and Authority of it out of themſelvs, and nothing from whatſoever had been done before.</p>
            <p>Next, there was no ſuch thing as <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Parliament</hi> in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it. As well <hi>Jack Cade,</hi> or <hi>Wat Tyler,</hi> if they had compleated their Rebellion, might have convened any party out of the People, calling it a <hi>Parliament,</hi> &amp; ſet himſelf up <hi>King;</hi> for one Subject hath as much Right to be <hi>King</hi> as any other.</p>
            <p>Next, ſuch a <hi>Parliament</hi> as it was, it was the Subject of an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; the Army of the Uſurper, by which he had got Poſſeſſion, and deſtroyed the <hi>King</hi>'s Power; ſo as in effect, condemning, depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, was the Act of the Army abſolutely; for ſo it muſt be done, by ſuch a party called a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and for the purpoſe; and ſo are all our Mock-ſhews, to ſet up any wickedneſs, own Authority, but act ſervilly, and are meer impoſture.</p>
            <p>Next, the Act, horrid Treaſon as was imaginable or poſſible to be in Nature: Now the Queſtion comes to be, Whether doing wickedly can create a lawfulneſs? If ſo, all ſins and villanies by the perpetrating them, loſe their Natures to be evils, and become lawful; A conceipt, nothing that comes into imagination can be more monſtrous! There muſt be a firſt lawfulneſs in every Act, elſe the doing it, is a Wickedneſs; and ſtill that wickedneſs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuated and multiplied in the after-acting it.</p>
            <p>Next, this condemned by the firſt <hi>Parliament</hi> that was upon the change of the Power; for ſo long as the Power continued it ſtood for good, as all Wickedneſs does. But the <hi>Parliament</hi> under the rightful <hi>King,</hi> damns it as traiterous, deteſtable, to be driven out
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53682:10"/>
of the World, never to riſe up again, pulling down God's Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon the Land, Civil War, and all the Plagues of it: I ſhall conclude this, that Wickedneſs can be no Preſident.</p>
            <p>Now, having gone along with him upon his particulars, which he only aſſerts, not proves; my next is, to take notice and mind him that he is very near loſing his cauſe, which I fear he will do anon; for he is arguing to a lawfulneſs in their putting the <hi>King</hi> to death, and it is his buſineſs to keep himſelf out of it; and likewiſe the <hi>Parliament's</hi> Cauſe, and War, and the Religion, Proteſtant and Presbyterian.</p>
            <p>Now, being himſelf a chief Profeſſor and Actor in thoſe-Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, if he finds Argument for it, ſo far it is his Reaſon; if his Reaſon, why not his Opinion (I know not the difference); if his Opinion, why not of the party: Thus he winds and ſcrues himſelf into that Intereſt he would diſclaim, and ſays more for it than the Actors themſelvs; and he concludes with theſe words, <hi>And they ſay,</hi> ſo as he ſayes it and yet makes it their ſaying.</p>
            <p>Either Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> holds it lawfully done or unlawfully; if law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, then he loſes his cauſe, which is a diſclamer of it as unlawful; if unlawfully, then his Judgment is, that Form of Law uſed to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Actions, makes them leſs evil.</p>
            <p>In Anſwer to it; This is an Opinion ſo ſtrange, that forms of Juſtice, put to wickedneſs to act it by, ſhould be the good of it, or make it a leſs evil, that I never heard it reaſoned, but condemned in Nature; very Nature it ſelf hath an abhorrency to it, when we ſee Laws, and Juſtice, and Tribunals, and any thing that is good in its ſelf to be made the means to wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>Now I ſhall enquire into the cauſes; Firſt, it is becauſe the Law is the Rule and meaſure of all Juſtice and Righteouſneſs, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the perverting of that begets a common Injuſtice, and this far exceeds the Nature of any particular evil, becauſe it refers and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to the common condition of men: All murdering by Law is moſt wicked and noxious, becauſe the Law it ſelf in its truth and righteouſneſs is murdered in it; and therefore great actions of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Injuſtice, the Laws drawn down to ſerve to them, are looked upon as Prodigies; and this Argument is ſuch as needs no ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication or addition to it, it contains all in it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Then the villany and apoſtacy of it, when it is done purpoſely of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53682:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
deſign and by Hypocriſy, this comprehends in it the complicate nature of Wickedneſs when Hypocriſy is added to it, and when that he calls Legal, Judicial, is made inſtrumental of it; the Law debauched, and bawded to ſerve to the intereſt of a wicked action; this is the very height of wickedneſs, it cannot in nature go high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. And hence it is, Hypocriſy, and falſe pretentions, and diſguiſing our corruptions with ſhews, and falſe owning of good, is ſo hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and abominable, and deteſted an agravation of all evil, and wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>It was an inſtance given in Parliament by the Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> upon the tryal of the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> to illuſtrate the nature of acting wickedneſs by Law, which they were going upon, that one ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving gotten with Child his Brothers Daughter, to mend the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and to his further end of enjoying her, marryes her; and this is condemned by the Caſuiſts, as adding to the ſimple ſin of Inceſt, by the Ordinance of Marriage abuſed to it. This ſhews the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it; but we ſhall find it higher preſidented in that of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both:</hi> The deſign being the having his Vineyard, the means muſt be ſuch as would ſerve to the end; a leſs means then to take away his life, would not do it; private murther will not ſerve, it muſt be ſuch a way as he muſt be condemned, and loſe his Inheritance with his life. The Elders of the City are plotted with in it; the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of a Faſt uſed; it muſt be done formally, Judicially; they gave Judgment, as appears, becauſe they received teſtimony, heard Witneſſes, then kill and poſſeſs. Nor this neither, though ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly wicked, riſes up to the heigth of the Kings Caſe; no para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel in the world for it.</p>
            <p>If it be objected, That they did not act deceitfully, but belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly, though wickedly; this is manifeſt againſt it, that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved the death of the King before they tryed him. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> cannot be ſo blinded with partiality, as to believe the King in any caſe ſhould have come off, or been acquitted, but precondemned; and thus to make him more the ſubject of their cruelties and ſcorn; and by a kind of Judgment, to be the fatal period of Kingſhip to the Nations; ſo as it was nothing but a direful deſign, dark as Hell, a meer conſpiracy; And Pagentry in the acting of it, and the Law abuſed to it, falſe in every part of it, to do it in the name of the People, and Parliament, ſo as in this, Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> reaſon utterly
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53682:11"/>
deſerts him, or elſe he contracts all the guilt, and odium of it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf, to extenuate the evil of the Act, by that which was the exquiſite wickedneſs of it, the formality and owning Authority in doing it.</p>
            <p>Then to deſcend from the evil in the nature of it to a politick conſideration of it; this goes to the Calling, the other but to the Perſon, this brings all Kings under their people: The difference betwixt this and that of the Pope is, Things may be as evil as is poſſible, yet not ſo extenſively evil; this is as univerſal as man is: for where men are, muſt be Government. This judicial way which he places as the good of it, is ſuch a Monſter in the preſident and practice of it, as all the World is concerned in it. It ſtrikes a greater blow then the killing of many Kings; the Calling killed in it; the priviledg and exemption of Supream Governours killed in it; the very eſſence of Government killed in it; the ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to God, and to be judged by none but God killed in it; all is beaten down and trampled upon by this act, the whole frame of nature over-turned; No ſuch thing as Government can be, if the governed may judg and execute their Governour.</p>
            <p>Then the manner of it by this formality, makes it viler upon the precious perſon of a Soveraign King than aſſaſſination, murdering, or ſudden diſpatching; The King to be ſubjected to ſo miſerable a condition, as to be made appear a criminal at the Tribunal of his Subjects: And if he had anſwered out of any poor, imbaſing hope, he had ſtained that ſacred Prerogative of Kings, Not to be judged: And all the tedious and odious formalities that did attend this, which horror makes me not expreſs, but take it inwardly, as that we owe the victims of our ſorrow to.</p>
            <p>To conclude it, I confeſs before this horrid production, I thought nothing could be worſe then that of the Pope: but now is the world of wickedneſs enlarged, and ſuch a Monſter as ſeems to add to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; the odium of it taints the Engliſh Nation, and will do as long as memory is of any thing: for he cannot deny it Engliſh, though ſo many out of it, ſo few in it.</p>
            <p>Now after all this, I do admire how Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> can diſpence with the Scriptures, againſt uſing force to Kings, or deſtroying them. His diſtinction of Parliamentary right will not ſerve, ſince it is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely forbidden.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:53682:11"/>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not revile the Gods, nor Curſe the Ruler of thy Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 22. ver. 28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That they may have to offer ſweet Odours to the God of Heaven, and pray for the Kings life and his Sons.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezr. 6.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This was cuſtomary with the Jews, to pray for the King; which being practicall in Gods Worſhip, was more then Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Againſt thee, thee only have I ſinned.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That is, None to judg the Kings ſin, but God: He might be evil, but the offence was only to God. The offence reſpected the Judg of it, which is God only.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Curſe not the King, no not in thy thought.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 10. ver. 20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This not thinking, is a reſtraint of all evill, ſince all evill is a firſt thinking evill; ſo as this is an univerſal prohibition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Son fear thou the Lord, and the King, and meddle not with the ſeditious, for their deſtruction ſhall riſe ſuddenly.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 24. ver. 21.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This proves the natural dependency of it, The fear of the King on the fear of God; then it goes to the reaſon of it, fear the King, not to rebel againſt him.</p>
            <p>I will conclude it with that of <hi>David,</hi> cautionary to his own Soul; <hi>Who can lay his hand on the Lords Annointed, and be guiltleſs?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 26. ver. 9.</note> A full definitive ſentence in the Caſe, that no violence can be offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a Kings perſon.</p>
            <p>And that this was general to all Kings, ſee the conſent of all Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the Higher Powers, for there is no Power but of God, and the Powers that be, are ordained of God; and whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reſisteth the Power, reſisteth the Ordinance of God; and they that reſist, receive to themſelves damnation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now that all theſe Powers doth properly intend a King, the words following are, <hi>For Princes are not to be feared for good works, but for evill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then after, in the ſingular number, <hi>He is the Miniſter of God, and he beareth not the Sword for nought.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this Text, as it makes ſubjection abſolute, ſo it takes away all parity of Powers; it intends one Supream. And Powers in the nature of it, is but one Power, for all ſubordinate Powers flow out of it, and refer to it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:53682:12"/>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.</note>
               <hi>Exhort therefore that first of all Supplications, Prayers, interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and giving of thanks, be made for all men, for Kings, and all that are in Authority, that we may live a peaceable life in all Godlineſſe and honesty; for that is good and acceptable in the ſight of God our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This preſent Emperour was a Tyrant, <hi>Claudius Nero,</hi> which ſtops all objection from the Kings miſ-uſing his Authority, it looks to the good of Government in general, and to the evil in general, of reſiſting to Government.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13.</note>
               <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unto Kings as Supream, or unto Governors, as unto them that are ſent of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here all Government is included in the King; ſent of him, that is out of him, and acts by him: And ſubmiſſion to Government here is made eſſential to Godlineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.17.</note>
               <hi>Fear God, Honour the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Making them connaturals, and that the fear of God cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt with diſhonouring the King; the word Honour includes all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection in it.</p>
            <p>Having taken forth theſe Scriptures thus clearly, and conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all the united force of them for preſervation of Kings, and for all Allegiance and fidelity to them, I reaſon thus, as to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and his Caſe, that the very force of Scripture, and Word of God, will not permit any ſuch thing to be, as a lawfulneſs of killing or jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging a King, or that poſſibly Law, or Authority amongſt men, ſhould be repugnant to the voice of God, being general and univerſal, for obedience to Kings, and not to offer violence to them; To ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg (as he needs muſt) that the Scripture commands ſuch things of Kings. But we have a Parliament, a thing made out of the people, that may lawfully condemn and execute the King; This is a meer contradiction to God himſelf: no pretence of man can diſſolve the univerſal Will of God, declared without exception; for a King he is, and no diſtinction can fruſtrate the will and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, for ſo it ſhould be ſubject to a lye if it ſhould come under man.</p>
            <p>And then to conſider, that truths ſtated in Moral duties, never loſe their natures, but are ever the ſame.</p>
            <p>And now I am loath yet to part with theſe Scriptures, till I have
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53682:12"/>
made a full claim to the ſenſe of them, howſoever Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> deal with them afterwards.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject, &amp;c.</hi> which is to the King, which I have proved, and the Text ſhews it; Is it not excluſive of any power, to be againſt the King? <hi>Every Soul;</hi> the word hath a ſtrange em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis in it; <hi>every Soul,</hi> that is, bringing it to a ſingularity, and nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt diſtinction of man by his Soul, which is moſt himſelf, and wherein he acts his ſubjection; and ſo preciſely, and individually, <hi>every,</hi> containing all.</p>
            <p>Then to fear the Lord and the King; that is both as one, the condition of the one implying the other. Then forbidding to joyn with ſeditious, or ſuch as are given to Change; which directly points out Rebellion: And then the caſe of very Tyrants, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding ſupplications to God for them, ſhewing directly the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Supream Governours to be born by the people, whatſoever their condition be. And then ſetting forth all Government of ſubordinates, to be but the Kings Government, virtually in him, nothing of themſelves <hi>perſe.</hi> And then, Curſe not the King, admit not an evil thought of him, pray for him; ſtill ſo many ſteps to his preſervation, keeping all harm or hurt far off him, muſt needs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the greateſt, of not deſtroying him: Then to call them Gods, an exemption from all humane Tribunalls, above the condition of mankind, ſubject to God onely; as Supream Governours cannot in nature be other: and then, generally ſubmiſſion to them for the Lords ſake; that is to ſay, Gods Service included in it.</p>
            <p>Now if out of all this we cannot make a conſtruction, that Kings ought not to be deſtroyed by the People, or by any ſort or calling of them under any Form, Guiſe, or pretence whatſoever; then no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be concluſive to man.</p>
            <p>If after all this, there be any thing for Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> to pretend to, and not utterly give up his cauſe, he muſt make the King of <hi>England</hi> to be ſuch a thing as not to be within the intendment of theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: Not a King, not a Supream Governour, not ſo qualified, or to be ſo obeyed, or acknowledged, a thing meerly nominal, and conditional, under ſome other Supremacy, and ſubject to a forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of himſelf; That this was ſo at his beginning, and admitting; that time and ſucceſſion hath given him no other right ſince; that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53682:13"/>
all this proves it ſelf ſo to be: That the Parliamentary was the onely Primary right, and only natural, and National, and Kings their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and Truſtees, and accomptable; And that the Government ſo began, when no King was, and his being ſtill under a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and the condition no leſs then to be ſubject to a lawful deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Power.</p>
            <p>If all this were, which is as far from truth as madneſs it ſelf; yet I think that God would take it ill that we ſhould mock him, to ſet up a King to Govern, and then to reſerve a Power to deſtroy him, againſt his Word, and meaning: for the very power of Governing inveſts him with all theſe rights of protection; vertually all theſe Attributes fall to him by his actual governing.</p>
            <p>It is a principle in nature, that Supremacy attracts all right to it, and all perfection: to be King, and not perfect, is impoſſible. And this I will ſay at laſt of the King himſelf, which I think his very ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and deſtroyers cannot deny, that never any Prince fell by his people, that had fewer faults, and more vertues.</p>
            <p>Now at laſt my exception to Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> is, that he perſonates the Proteſtants, ſo as to deſtroy them, and their Religion. There is no other way of keeping the guilt and imputation of that horrid ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed act from the Religion, but by a total condemnation of it. We ſay, and juſtly, that it was an act that tranſcends all that ever was, worſe and more infernal, and execrable, then any thing elſe the Pope or man can do.</p>
            <p>Now Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> out of his particular, makes it the Proteſtant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, that it be not ſo evil as the wickedneſs under the Religion of Papiſts, and ſo puts it upon the Proteſtants account, of whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver nature it be, and makes it their intereſt to extenuate the evil of it, which is a meer involving them, and their cauſe into it, and the moſt unjuſt in the World; for, Is a Religion to anſwer for what wickedneſs men do in it: I mean, being of it, or profeſſing it? But thus he loves to hale all Intereſts after him, to follow his ſenſe. Let him himſelf be in love with it, extenuate it, find Jeſuitical abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, quinteſſential notions, to diſſolve all Allegiance upon Terms, let him take it to himſelf, and not make it more general then his own party.</p>
            <p>Having done with this ſad ſubject, we will ſee him in his next, whither he will lead us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:53682:13"/>Object. <hi>It is a grievous Caſe, that the Senate or Body of a Nation ſhould think themſelvs neceſſitated to defend themſelvs, and the Church and State, againſt their Prince, or any that act by his Commands; it will ſtrongly tempt them to think that the end is to be preferred before the means; and, it ceaſeth to be a means which is againſt or deſtructive to the end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The poor unfortunate <hi>King,</hi> that could never by any poſſible compliance and means begg off his own and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms ruine of them, was wont to tell them, when they uſed the great Argument of neceſſity for all violent actions, that they were neceſſities of their own making. Becauſe their ends were exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, and ſuch as the Laws would not bear, they muſt proportion the means, which drew on the neceſſities.</p>
            <p>Now to his preferring the end before the means; a principle he is fallen upon, and the moſt dangerous one of the World; for by this he may decline all Truth and Juſtice, to go the next way over to his ends: and yet a very ſtrong one, that the end is that for which the means is; there is no uſe or conſideration of the means, but to the end: By this ground he hath laid flat all Honeſty, Truth, Goodneſs, whatſoever; for it may be it doth not ſuit to the end. And hence it was, that their ends being Reformation (as they call our Deformation and Deſtruction) it could not be done by a leſſe means: I do but mind him of this, his party having made ſo much uſe of it. The truth is, if men would ty themſelvs to the Juſtice of the means, they could never attain to unjuſt ends.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>It is eſſentiall to governing Power to be for common good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> No doubt but it is, as appears by their deſtroying the Government, and we never had any good ſince. But without ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this advantage, I will give him a further Anſwer, from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Government, and every other thing we call good; that is, good in the generality, not exact good in every action of it.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>It is no Authority which is uſed againſt common good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Then there is no Authority in the World; for there is no Authority or Magiſtracy, but at ſome time or other is uſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. He multiplies forward ſtill,</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>It would tempt them alſo to think that God never gave Power to any againſt himſelf, or above his Laws, or againſt the end of Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:53682:14"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> He ſhould prove here, that God gave them a Right of deſtroying both the King and the Government; for that is the Caſe: For he confeſſeth the War raiſed by themſelvs againſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent Subjects.</p>
            <p>But to anſwer to this, as he intends it; God doth ſome times give evil Governours, and doth he not likewiſe give them Power? God himſelf fore-ſpake in <hi>Saul,</hi> and then concluded the People, in theſe words; <hi>then,</hi> that is, when they were oppreſſed by their King,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 8.18. Grotius de jure Belli, 81.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall they cry out;</hi> that is to ſay, ſeek help of God (<hi>Quia ſcilicet humana remedia nulla extarent, Grotius</hi> expoſition of it) <hi>call to God for help;</hi> that is, there was no means of reſiſtance to be uſed on their part. His next,</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>A Senate, or the Body of a Nation, will be apt to think themſelvs fit to diſcern when the Publick ſafety is dangerouſly aſſaulted, and will hardly be brought to truſt any one to be the finall Judge of their neceſſity; as thinking, ſuch a publick neceſſity proves it ſelf, and needs no Judge but ſenſe and reaſon to diſcern it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Suppoſe there had been no Parliament, this Argument would have ſerved for the Body of the People to riſe up, and take away the <hi>King</hi>'s Power, as not fit to judge of the neceſſity, or to be truſted with the Publick ſafety.</p>
            <p>It was the <hi>King</hi>'s Act to call a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and 'twas his and our ruine that he put himſelf upon it.</p>
            <p>Having hitherto kept equal pace with him in theſe his ſeverall diſtinct heads, give me leave in general to cenſure of them; that is, that in them he hath ſown the ſeeds of all the Rebellions in the World: Let them be taken as truths, abſtractedly, without their alloy or compoſition, (as ſo the very Elements would deſtroy us,) no Government can ſtand. Do we not, as often as we err in any thing, employ the means againſt the end? and ſhall we, as often, fall out with our ſelvs? Theſe abſtracted Conſiderations cannot conſiſt with the being of Man, which is not certain in any thing, but ſubject to error; and as often as ever a <hi>King</hi> errs, ſo often, by his Argument, the means is againſt the end, and loſeth the eſſence of a governing Power. So as by Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Learning, there can never want matter for Rebellion.</p>
            <p>In the next, he raiſeth his <hi>Parliament</hi> as an out-work to affront and batter Monarchy, in theſe words,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:53682:14"/>Object. <hi>And if they alſo think, that the fundamentall Conſtitution of the Government doth make the Senate the higheſt Judge of the ſafety or danger of the Re-publick; and that it is Treaſon againſt the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, and (as Politicians ſay) againſt the</hi> Majeſtas realis, <hi>to riſe againſt them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath of this in ſeveral places, the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>'s Supremacy, it is his <hi>Goliath:</hi> I ſhall anſwer generally to it at once.</p>
            <p>Now the Arguments may be many, I will make it but a Paſſage, not a ſerious Debate, and give but hints of truths that may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, that I am ſure, though I was not of that time, that <hi>Kings</hi> were when <hi>Parliaments</hi> were not; and then, muſt be granted abſolute, the other not in being: We cannot ſuppoſe here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> any time of Government without <hi>Kings,</hi> and the <hi>Kings</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs thought it beſt to convene the People, to draw thereby aids of the Publick, by publick conſent; and likewiſe, to have all Counſels and all Grievances in common; to be common in helps and means which is ſtrongeſt; and peradventure, to ballance the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds by this popular Power.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever the ends were in it, or the uſe to be made of it, or accidents that grew out of it, it ſhews it was a Creature mearly of the King's Will and creating; and therefore cannot be intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but to act under him, and to his help, as the end of its Being: So being called by the King in this ſenſe, they bear in them the Peoples Rights, whatſoever was left in the People to be diſpoſed of by their own conſent: Their Power therefore muſt hold pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion with that; that is, only in the quality of the People, as to complain of Grievances, and petition Redreſſes, to give their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate to the Publick, and to conſent to alter Fundamentals as there ſhall be cauſe; all which are the natural Rights of the People, and common conſent is required to them.</p>
            <p>Now this does not reach at all to Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s ſenſe of ſharing with the <hi>King</hi> in Supremacy, and Power, and right of governing nothing at all of it. All <hi>Parliament</hi> rights have their ſtation below governing, it is by accident when they meddle with the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as about the cauſes that require their help. And all great,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53682:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and outward relations, and inward, may be Objects of this great Body of the People, as their help is required; but this with that caution, as the King puts them on, and takes them off: So jealous a thing is Soveraignty it ſelf.</p>
            <p>And it is a nice diſtinction to make them Judges of the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and not to judge of the cauſe of the neceſſity; and therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve themſelvs ſometimes in it too far, and the retreats have been difficult. No doubt, this muſt needs be a ſtrange, great, conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Power in the conſequence of it, that which all the reſt moves by, and is the matter or means of the Government: But this does not alter the Nature of it.</p>
            <p>It is a moſt noble Conſtitution, becauſe it begets treatment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Prince</hi> and People; and there is a correſpondency betwixt the giving of the one, and the retribution of the other; but when either make too much uſe of their Power it deſtroys the order, and the inconvenience is ſo intolerable to the Nation, as they are brought again to it, and muſt correſpond.</p>
            <p>Now nothing preſervs ſo much as when things keep to their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. The good of <hi>Parliaments</hi> does conſiſt within their own rights, and not to enter into the <hi>King</hi>'s; for then it breaks the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> or the <hi>Parliament</hi> breaks the Government.</p>
            <p>To return to the nature of the Objection of co-ordinate Power of <hi>Parliaments;</hi> The <hi>Parliament</hi> is a Creation that comes out of the <hi>King</hi>'s Will and Power; nothing of Power to beget it ſelf; and therefore cannot be underſtood to ſerve to another end, againſt that which was its cauſe, and which it ſelf had abſolute Being without it.</p>
            <p>Never to this day, they have Power to their own Being, but at the <hi>King</hi>'s Will; a meer Entity firſt in the <hi>King</hi>'s Will, before it can have any in them; ſo as they are meerly Creatures, having their Creation from another's Will, and ſo to determine them after they are in being, which ſhews the moſt abſolute depending on an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Power that poſſibly can be.</p>
            <p>Hence rationally, and conſequently of this it muſt be, that the end is of the Agent and Author, and not to be their own end, that did not, nor could not, move to their own Being; ſo as meerly it follows, A <hi>Parliament</hi> is the <hi>King</hi>'s buſineſs becauſe it flows out of his Will: And ſome Acts have been made by conſent of <hi>Kings</hi> for certainty of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> but have not bound <hi>Kings;</hi> for we
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53682:15"/>
ſee, they have been diſcontinued many years together: So certain it is, that Regal Right cannot be reſtrained.</p>
            <p>Now, the <hi>King</hi>'s good and the People's, are ſo neceſſarily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, as it cannot be ſuppoſed they can ſerve the <hi>King,</hi> but it muſt conſerve the Kingdom, and all the People: And hence flows all publick conſiderations and concluſions; the whole Intereſt of the Nation reſolves it ſelf into it, and all the Powers ſubmit to it; becauſe all parties are in it by convention or repreſentation, and the <hi>King</hi> can make lawful whatſoever they can conſent to.</p>
            <p>But without the <hi>King</hi> they are a meer inanimate Body, and can act nothing; they are as the Womb or Matrix, the <hi>King</hi> is the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerative Maſculine part, that gives life and production, and actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates and forms their conceptions.</p>
            <p>And the difference not rightly conceived begets the miſtake, confounding their Power with that of ordinary ſtanding Courts, which act by the <hi>King</hi>'s Power inveſted in them, which he cannot with-draw, or deny to; and this of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> which is extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and by the <hi>King</hi>'s conſent. And then too, their work is about the generality, not to do with the ordinary proceedings of Law proper to other Courts, but only the abuſe of them.</p>
            <p>The Author of the Hiſtory of <hi>Independency</hi> affirms, <hi>pag.</hi> 35.<note place="margin">Hiſtory of Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, 35.</note> that the judicial Power of the Houſe of Lords is by the King's ſpecial Authority: his Argument upon it is, The <hi>King</hi> makes them Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrators and interpreters of his Laws, but he never truſts any but himſelf with the Power of pardoning, and diſpenſing with the rigour of the Law, in Criminal caſes: And though the Lord Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is Speaker of the Lord's Houſe of courſe, yet he is no Member of the Lord's Houſe, <hi>virtute Officii.</hi> The Judges are not Members but Aſſiſtants only; ſo that no man in the Houſe of Peers, as he is ſimply a Peer, is truſted by the King, either by diſpenſation of Law or Equity.</p>
            <p>When a Peer of Parliament, or any man elſe is tryed before the Lords in <hi>Parliament,</hi> criminally, he cannot be tried by his Peers only, becauſe in acts of Judicature there muſt be a Judge Superior, who muſt have his Inferiors miniſterial to him: Therefore in the Trial of the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> as in all other Trials upon Life and Death in the Lord's Houſe, the King grants his Commiſſion to a Lord High Steward to ſit as Judge, and the reſt of the Lords are but
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53682:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in the nature of Jurors; ſo that it is the <hi>King</hi>'s Commiſſion that authorizeth and diſtinguiſheth them.</p>
            <p>When a Writ of Error iſſueth out of the <hi>Chancery</hi> to the Houſe of Peer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, they derive their Authority meerly from that Writ: For the three Reaſons aforeſaid, the Houſe of Peers is no Court of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture at all without the King's ſpecial Authority granted to them ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by his Writ, or his Commiſſion.</p>
            <p>As for the Houſe of Commons, they never pretended to any Power of Judicature, and have not ſo much Authority as to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter an Oath. Thus far his,</p>
            <p>But the Argument is not at all pertinent as to the Houſe of Lords whom they have expelled, and all Form of Parliament or Callings, but in the People; their ground is onely upon a Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, as the People's Repreſentatives. Nevertheleſs, we take the whole, and give truly the Nature of a Parliament; for the perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt way of rejecting Falſhood is by delineating the true Form.</p>
            <p>It is not imaginable for a King to govern without the aſſiſtance and aſſent of the Peers, for Government cannot ſtand alone; for as they are ever a party, where any King is: the Queſtion is only of the Commons,<note place="margin">Prin's plea for Lords, pag. 182.</note> which is an Adjunct; and therefore the Search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers into Antiquity take upon them to antedate them, and derive them but as an Accident to the Government in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to take it in the whole, it being a truly poiſed Government and mixed Intereſt, hath left ſo great a ſhare in the People as ſervs to treat their <hi>King</hi>'s with, and be at all times able to gain conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: And God forbid any Power ſhould deny to the People's good; it can be no end of Government, and therefore he is not ſingle or alone, but hath common conſent in the great Intereſts of the Nation, changing or making Laws, or making impoſitions; He muſt have common conſent to this, and this draws all the reſt to it, ſince hardly any thing can move but by theſe two Intereſts; and this is the ballance of the Government, to make it hang equal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Prince</hi> and People.</p>
            <p>And the evils and miſchief that ſometimes redounds is from the abuſe of it, not from the Nature of it, being the beſt compoſition of Government in the World, and the People freer under it than in any Common-wealth Government, which they call free Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; the Reaſon is a Secret till looked into <hi>Phyſically,</hi> that is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53682:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
this (beſt of all to be ſeen in our late, long, odious, <hi>Parliament</hi>), there all the People's Liberties were ſwallowed up, the People un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creatured as it were, no defenſive, all in the <hi>Parliament;</hi> when as in the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> the People have a direct party, and a defenſive, as there ſhall be cauſe, againſt any deprivation of their Rights.</p>
            <p>There are ſome Signals of Kingly abſolute Right, which need but naming, as the King's <hi>Adviſeray,</hi> to Bills which he will not paſs, which was ever effectual, as to a total condemnation.</p>
            <p>So as here was no Power out of the <hi>King,</hi> all reduced to him in his laſt Power of denying, and likewiſe of pardoning. And this needs not plead any right for it, but right of Nature, in reaſon of Government, elſe without ſuch a Power the <hi>King</hi> might be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to nothing. And a <hi>King</hi> never falls or loſeth his Power, but he is loſt in himſelf too: He does not retain <hi>Kingly</hi> Government but on condition to periſh with it.</p>
            <p>And therefore all Laws are ſtyled of Grace, and petitioned for; becauſe the People, till they are paſſed the Royal aſſent, have but a Right in Reaſon to them, not in Law; only from the Supream Law of <hi>Salus Populi,</hi> which is the comprehenſive of all Laws.</p>
            <p>The common miſtake is, becauſe the King cannot do ſuch and ſuch things without the Parliament, <hi>Ergo,</hi> The Parliament governs the King. Now, as to this, Many may be ſaid to govern me, ſo as to reſtrain me, that I cannot go beyond my own Power, and yet this no active governing Power over another; this is the eaſieſt thing to conception that can come into imagination. Is there not, where any Right is, which we call property, a power of denying? And this is all the abſolute Parliamentary power, conſidered divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dedly from the King; and this vaſt inconſequence, containing all the means almoſt to be King, unleſs the King would break throw it, which is the hardeſt task any King can go about; yet nothing of the Nature of governing power, no agency or efficiency in it by it ſelf, but only a meer Negative. Becauſe I am engaged in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, I will reſort back to the ſtate of the Queſtion, of a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to be the higheſt Judge of the ſafety, or danger of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick: The Anſwer is direct, that the King is the ſole Judge of the ſafety or danger of the Re-publick; as King he is only truſted,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53682:17"/>
and there cannot be two ſuch judging powers; for then there can be no determination, when they ſtand in competition.</p>
            <p>Therefore all the Powers in the Kingdom act ſubordinately to the King, and not againſt or athwart the King's Power, for that were for a Being to deſtroy it ſelf.</p>
            <p>The diſtinction lies in this, that they have nothing to do with the King's Power, but the People's Rights; which they diſpoſe of by the King's conſent, and not abſolutely at all out of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs.</p>
            <p>In this they may oppoſe the King's deſire; that is, they have a Negative Power, not to be compelled, or the People to be put out of poſſeſſion without them.</p>
            <p>But where the diſagreement is, they are to acquieſce, and ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing comes of it, and the King fails of his end; this is the height of their power.</p>
            <p>Their Bills, which they are free to make, contain in them Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances to be reformed, which implies complaint and conſent; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the King cannot do by his quality ſingly as King, he doth by conſent of the People; and that is the Character of a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the People; for it directly repreſents the Univerſality, the People; and hath directly and truly no power but what is natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally and naturally the People's, ſo as look upon that, you find this, and no difference at all in it; hence conſenting and denying, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, aiding, being natural properties of Rights, are left to them, as the People in them: And this, though great, as to all the means of governing, it doth not come near it; ſo vaſt a difference is betwixt being free in mine own, and having Power over anothers, as no reaſon needs to be given of it.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, the King, as the common Intereſt, is not to be ſuppoſed deficient of the Publick means; that were unnatural: therefore as to Government it ſelf, all means are lawful; nor any thing ſo concerning to the People, as to keep the tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for when they deſtroy that, they loſe the means to their own good.</p>
            <p>I might leave it here in its cauſes, but I ſhall ſay ſomething by way of Preſident.</p>
            <p>Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the greateſt Courter of her People, and yet the beſt Governour, would loſe nothing of her Prerogative; ſhe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:53682:17"/>
did every thing with her Parliament as with Subjects; they knew their own buſineſs, and ſhe would keep them to it; and abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the better for their obedience, for every thing is good or evil as it is governed.</p>
            <p>Not a Faſt, or Humiliation day, or Preaching,<note place="margin">His Plea for the Lords, p. 409.</note> as learned Mr. <hi>Prin</hi> hath given the recital of it, that they could ſet up for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but ſhe would check it, and bring them to Humiliation for it.</p>
            <p>So dangerous a wiſe Prince ſees it, popular liberty but to begin to creep out. They had eſſayes upon her about Marriage: ſhe would not admit the preſſure upon her, nor ſuffer them to be Judg in it.</p>
            <p>Then after, that of her Succeſſor; that went nearer to her,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Camden's</hi> An a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, Elizb.</note> a pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching thought, and in this the repulſe of them was harder, becauſe apparently did depend upon it the ſafety, or danger of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms after her; yet in this, ſhe was reſolved 'twas too precious to her to part with it to them, kept it to the laſt hour of her life; when ſhe could live no longer, then ſhe declared a Succeſſor, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Members that promoted it, laid abſolute peremptory com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand upon the Houſe againſt it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pryn</hi>'s Plea for the Lords, p. 410, 411.</note> at other times impriſoned their Members, and would uſually tell them, when they exceeded, that it was in Her to give them being, and to diſſolve their being, and to aſſent and diſſent to any thing done in Parliament. This from the beſt and wiſeſt of Princes; well knowing, that it is not poſſible for a Prince to be juſt to the People, without true obedience from the people.</p>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> his time, by ſome Paſſages then in the Parliaments, will ſhew us the difference betwixt Regal Right, and Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Right. Parliament 5 <hi>James,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Raw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi>'s reſult from Sir <hi>Francis Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con,</hi> p. 38, 39.</note> the Earl of <hi>Salisburyes</hi> words to a Committee of the Houſe; That matter of War or Peace, was <hi>Arcanum Imperii,</hi> and muſt be kept within the vail; nevertheleſs that ſometimes, Parliaments have been made acquainted with mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of War and Peace, in a generality; but it was upon one of theſe two motives, when the King and Councel conceived, that either it was material to have ſome declaration of the zeal, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the people; or elſe when the King needed to demand monies, and aids, for the charge of the War. The Earl of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton,</hi> at the ſame time, another of the Council of State, that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:53682:18"/>
both by Philoſophy, and Civil Law, <hi>Ordinatio belli et pacis, eſt abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luti Imperii.</hi> He further reaſoned, That the compoſition of the Houſe of Common, was meerly Democratical, and intended to have a private and local Wiſedome, as to the places that ſent them, and not fit to examine ſecrets of State, which depend upon varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of circumſtances; and although there be divers Gentlemen in the mixture of the Houſe, that are of good capacity, and inſight in matters of State, yet that was the accident of the perſon, not the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the place; and things are to be taken in the inſtitution, not in the practice.</p>
            <p>The Parliament of the 18th of King <hi>James,</hi> was a Parliament of conteſt and diſpute; and held out long by an able King, and a ſevere People. It was an effectual Parliament as to the granting of Subſidies, and reforming abuſes, yet in the end thrown off. The evills that it had to work upon, were the evils of Peace, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king danger of Religion a Monſter; and looking at it through the glaſs of their own Paſſions, would dictate extreams to the King about it, and the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> match formidable; and the Kings unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes from Parliaments, had put him upon petty helps, as liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, Monopolies: about thoſe bred no breach, but was matter ſerved them to work upon, and wholly put to them, and the perſons offenders in it expoſed, and the King himſelf a chief actor to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it: And to pull down the Chancellor <hi>Bacon</hi> for Bribery, was their work; yet at laſt, it had not a legal end of a Parliament, but diſſolved by Proclamation, and Crimination. The King enforced to this: for this King never acted to publick offence by his Paſſion, but meerly his neceſſity. Therefore I ſhall reſort back, and take ſome remarks and paſſages of the proceedings along with me, to find where the ſtone of it was.</p>
            <p>After the matter of the puniſhments were over, the great and high conſiderations, as for diverſion of the Match with <hi>Spain,</hi> and declaring war againſt that King for the Palatinate, and new deviſed preſſures upon Papiſts, and preſſing executions of Laws upon them; ſo as they involve all the Kings Intereſt into their hands, under the notion, that it was the Kingdomes Intereſt. The King hearing of this, and it beating thorow his ſides, betakes himſelf to high reſolution; and to prevent the prejudice of receiving it formally from them, writes thus to the Speaker.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:53682:18"/>
               <hi>Theſe are to command You to make known in Our Name unto the Houſe, that none therein ſhall preſume henceforth, to meddle with any thing concerning Our Government, or deep matters of State; and namely, not to deal with Our deareſt Son's Match with the Daughter of</hi> Spain, <hi>and alſo not to meddle with any mans particulars, which have their due mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Our ordinary Courts of Juſtice. And whereas we hear they have ſent a Meſſenger to Sir</hi> Edwin Sandis, <hi>to know the reaſons of his late reſtraint, You ſhall in Our Name reſolve them, That it was not for any miſdemeanor of his in Parliament. But, to put them out of doubt of any queſtion of that nature that may ariſe among them hereafter, You ſhall reſolve them in Our Name, That we think Our ſelves very free, and able to puniſh any mans miſdemeanors in Parliament, as well during their Sitting, as after.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their Anſwer by way of Petition to the King: firſt Palliating over, and with the manner and inducements to go upon ſuch things, they have theſe words; <hi>In the diſcourſe whereof we did not aſſume to our ſelves, any power to determine of any part thereof, nor intrude upon the Sacred bounds of your Royall Authority; to whom, and to whom only, we acknowledg it doth belong to Reſolve of Peace and War, and of the Marriage of the moſt Noble Prince, your Son; but as your moſt loyal and humble Subjects and Servants, repreſenting the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of your Kingdome, who have a large intereſt in the happy, and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous Eſtate of your Majeſty, and your Royal Poſterity, and of the flouriſhing Eſtate of Our Church, and Common-wealth; did reſolve, out of our cares, and fears, truly and plainly, to demonſtrate theſe things to your Majeſty, which we were not aſſured could otherwiſe come ſo ſafely, and clearly to your knowledg; and that being done, to lay the ſame down at your Majesties feet, without expectation of any other anſwer of your Majeſty touching theſe higher points, then what at your good pleaſure, and in your own time ſhould be held fit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if we do but make a breathing ſpace, and a ſtop here, or being like getting to ſome heighth of ground look about us, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it ſhews, that no Supremacy is pretended to, but utterly diſclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; and all reſolving, determining, or the laſt power in buſineſs of Government; and no perſons can come lower, or aſſert more extreamly, and exemplarly againſt themſelves in any ſuch point of Right. So as we ſee plainly, Governing Power is all with the King; and the queſtion comes to be only about propounding, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:53682:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
diſcourſing, upon thoſe high points of Regal power in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, not being ſpecially required to it; which Kings think, comes too near their skirts, like <hi>David,</hi> cutting off a lap of King <hi>Saul</hi>'s Garment, to ſhew only, that he was in his power; ſo Kings think the one cannot be done, or aſſumed, that is entering into, or aſſuming out of ſelf Authority, to treat of the very eſſentialls about Government, or the great weighty occaſions that refer to it, but like the cutting off of the lap of the Garment, begets a power over the perſon; and this was the very ſtone of difference in this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; ſo as we ſee to how neer a point it is reduced, a little ſpace or difference, one would think, betwixt propoſing only, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out power of reſolving, and not propoſing; now there is nothing more ſatisfactory then the Kings own anſwer to them about this; for no perſon could ſpeak his buſineſs ſo well as himſelf, and this very particular of the paſſage, it is a School of Learning. Now becauſe I will not altogether write out of another, nor be tedious, I omit it: It is no matter, let it be amongſt <hi>arcana imperii,</hi> not to bring all into vulgar light, elſe the reaſons might be abſtracted why Parliaments are not of themſelves to aſſume to treat of the points proper to the King in Government. I ſhall leave this, and only excuſe my ſelf in it, being far too high for me, that I only do it in the defenſive to regal Right, which is higher, and to the peoples right, which does not conſiſt in confuſion of Government, but in the certainty of it.</p>
            <p>Having done with this high conſideration, I ſhall take notice of his dangerous inſerted words, of <hi>Majestas Realis;</hi> the ſelf ſame as condemned in the <hi>Spencers,</hi> in <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. his time, and likewiſe in the following Parliaments of that Age, for the moſt deſtructive de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign againſt the perſons, and ſafety of Kings, that ever was imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. A dividing of the Kings perſon, and his end of Governing; they would have the Majeſty to conſiſt in the end, and ſo diviſeable from the perſon; and ſo the King might be depoſed and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and yet the Majeſty whole. What will not mans brain hatch, when he is diſpoſed to be wicked? This was new forged, brought out of the Mint again, and begot the Notion, of Treaſon againſt the Common-Wealth, and ſerved to make the King a Traytor. I deſire his patience to read Sir <hi>Edward Cook,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o.</hi> 7. Rep. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lv.</hi> Caſe.</note> 7. Report, <hi>Calvins</hi> Caſe; there he will tell him that all Allegiance is tyed, and refers
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:53682:19"/>
to the perſon of the King; that the whole conſiſtency of Majeſty, and Kingſhip, muſt be in a perſon in being, not to hang in the Ayre, as an accident without his ſubject; all Relation, all Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, all Majeſty, are but rayes from that body, dividedly from the King, can be no conſideration at all of Treaſon, or Majeſty; this Serpenti e way of creeping betwixt the Kings perſon and his Authority was a device to deſtroy him.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>When the Legiſlative Power, and higheſt judicial Power, is by the conſtitution of the Government, divided between the Prince and the Senate, and ſo the Soveraignty divided, many will be ready to think with</hi> Grotius, <hi>de jure belli Lib.</hi> 1.13. <hi>pag.</hi> 91. That the Prince inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Senate's Right, may juſtly be reſiſted, and may loſe his Right: <hi>quod locum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Grotius, habere cenſeo etiam ſi dictum ſit belli poteſtatem penes Regem fore; id enim de bello externo intelligendum est, cum alioqui, quiſquis imperii ſummi partem habeat non poteſt non jus habere eam partem tuendi; quod ubi fit, poteſt Rex etiam, ſuam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perii partem, belli jure amittere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe parties will ſtill ſtumble at the ſame ſtone; that is, becauſe of the Legiſlative power, in ſome ſort, or manner, or form of it, in the Parliament, therefore the Supremacy: which does not follow, for the Supremacy is the ſole Governing Power, and Government is a conſtant being, the other but at times, and by occaſion; ſo as no proportion at all is betwixt a conſtant gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Power, and an occaſional Power; and when they are deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded but about their own Rights; it being planted in Nature, that where Right is, there is a power of denying, and a power of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, yielding, and conſenting; and this is the Parliamentary power properly, and <hi>per ſe,</hi> all which ariſes out of the Rights, and property of the People meerly. Now theſe perſons will not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the difference betwixt the power of conſenting (which muſt needs be likewiſe a power of denying), and active, efficient pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which is in Government it ſelf, and is alwayes conſtant and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal: It has the properties, as the Soul in the Animal, cannot have parts in it, and dividedneſs, or to diſcontinue.</p>
            <p>Now they introduce this their objection with a <hi>When,</hi> when it is ſo, that is, the Soveraignty divided; they ſhould prove where it is ſo: I think not in nature of two Soveraign Powers in one Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: certainly this is no Government, but diſtinct Governments;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:53682:20"/>
and how it can refer to one people governed, requires the inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for when they ſtand upon terms of difference, then the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment preſently is in the ſtate of War, and none to reconcile it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing equal divided Powers. Rights may lye ſo, but Governing Power cannot lye ſo; the diſtance is the ſame as betwixt two For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign States, or Princes, who may reconcile, and accommodate their reciprocal good ſo long as they can accord upon it, as well as theſe ſeveral diſtinct Powers in one body; and in this, either party up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the difference, betakes himſelf to his defenſive, and then the Government ceaſes to be; ſo as it is not at all conſiſtent with the nature of Government, but of Governments, in reſpect the one of the other.</p>
            <p>All Governments are either Monarchial Governments, or mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Governments; now in Monarchical Government, firſt it ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes abſoluteneſs of Supremacy in the Monarch or Prince, and then it cannot ſuppoſe it likewiſe in any other, for then the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſhould be a Monſter of two heads; and beſides, ſo can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not act, the Powers in counterpoiſe being equal, and ſo it is no Power, but a Power of deſtroying it ſelf; as equal contraries when they meet, are deſtructive to the matter that is the ſubject of them. Peradventure ſome inſtances may be found of ſome that have been called Kings, and have been but head Members of Common-wealths, and ſuch, their ſafety and being is to act ſubordinately to the Powers of the Common-Wealth, not above them, for ſo preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they ſhould periſh, having no power abſolute to defend them; ſo as we ſee directly, it muſt be one or other, either Subordination, or Supremacy entire.</p>
            <p>That muſt needs be a ſtrange Government, where the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty is divided, and lying in divers Powers, when they differ, the people diſtracted in their obedience, not knowing where to obey to, but made to follow the luſts, appetites, and injuſtice of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther party, as it gains power, and not certain to retain it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is a Law amongſt our Statute Laws of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">H. 7.11. y. C. 1.</note> That the ſubject ſhall be ſecured to fight for the King in being. This meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from this reaſon of avoiding the miſchief the Subject is put to, by a divided commanding Power; this Law, though a groſs one, and againſt truth many times, becauſe Uſurpers did poſſeſs the Throne, yet for this reaſon preferred, and not yet deſtroyed; though the Sword was too hard for it, as for all things elſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:53682:20"/>It is to be obſerved, that there is no Government without a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which makes Rights in the People; God himſelf doth not govern the World otherwiſe ſo, but that he gives the People Laws both for their direction and conviction; for it is, in ſome ſenſe, that the Law makes the offence; and beſides, otherwiſe all muſt flow from the King as Water continually renewed out of its Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and the People not know whom to obey, nor ſubordinates how to act; ſo as mixture in the Government makes no Argument, it being of neceſſity to all Governments.</p>
            <p>And as for taking up Arms, and fighting for their Rights; Right and right of defending holds not againſt Government abſolutely. His next.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>If a Prince engage either hired Strangers, or Fugitives, or home-bred Delinquents, or others, to riſe up againſt the Senate or Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, either it is lawful to defend themſelvs by Arms, or not; if not, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if they have a ſhare in the Soveraignty, then is his Power abſolute and unlimited, and neither Laws, or any thing below, are any ſecurity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Will to the common ſafety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Ages that follow ſhall be very little beholden to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> to let them know the true ſtate of a buſineſs of the higheſt and moſt horrid importance that ever befell <hi>England,</hi> far excelling in accurſedneſs the inteſtine War betwixt the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> becauſe it hath deſtroyed our Form of Government, and all Title to Govern; which is an unhappineſs upon a People above all evill whatſoever, Uſurpation being a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſource of evil.</p>
            <p>I admire he can be ſo little ſerious in it; This of his ſeems no more, then that the King raiſeth wicked Forces to deſtroy the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; and a Queſtion meerly, Whether or no they ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelvs.</p>
            <p>There is a great Narrative and Hiſtorical part belongs to this, to ſet it forth; But it was not my end, but only ſo far as to anſwer his, and no farther.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, the Parliament made alliance with the <hi>Scots,</hi> diſbanded the Engliſh Army, to work their end upon the King. The King was taken in a Toyl of his own making, calling a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Scottiſh Army being in <hi>England;</hi> and now both Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts claſped him, that he had no means left him to get out of it,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:53682:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
but to break thorow it by force, which he deſpaired of. They draw up a Remonſtrance to the three Nations, to ſhame the King to the People, and make him odious; not the accidents of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment but are put upon the King's ſcore; as if any Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment could be without faults, and as if we ſhould have been ſo much happier under them, under whom we have found the little finger heavier than the Loyns of Kings, and their whippings Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions to the other's Rods; an Inſtance taken from Scripture, and often applyed, but never truer than in this of our condition and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering under them.</p>
            <p>The Parliament once in, ruine was inevitable upon the King, never after was any wiſdom or means uſeful to him; preſervation is not always in our own Power, we have but the offer of it, which neglected or omitted, commonly the means turns to another Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and cannot be regained. The King did now, too late, ſtrive by all manner of conceſſions and compliance, yet nothing would divert deſtructin that did fix upon him, like the poyſoned Shirt prepared by <hi>Dejanira</hi> for <hi>Hercules,</hi> which once on, though he did ſtrive to tear it from him, yet to no purpoſe; the venom and poyſon, and fiery quality of it, did penetrate into great <hi>Hercules,</hi> and conſume him.</p>
            <p>The truth is, the King was diſpoſſeſſed before he durſt appear in oppoſition; all his Forces by Sea and Land, City of <hi>London, Hull,</hi> and Port-Towns, engaged againſt him; his own Ordnance and Arms to fight againſt him: He had nothing but the Intereſt of a King, and the pity of thoſe few that did compaſſionate him, (the People generally poyſoned,) to raiſe up any party for him, and fighting was but his meer neceſſity; for, as he ſaid himſelf, he was ſure to be the loſer, becauſe he had nothing but his own to oppoſe to in his own Kingdom, and his own People his Enemies. Yet further, no Conceſſions would ſerve, and Conceſſions were his fault and misfortune too; it comes to be the caſe of the King not to be truſted, and ſo the diſpute grew upon the <hi>Militia;</hi> a word intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, commonly treated, as if an ordinary thing, no leſs in it ſelf, than the being of a King, who ſhould have the Power. I may ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well give it off here, becauſe the caſe came to be, Whether King or no King.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:53682:21"/>This being ſomewhat of the active part, I ſhall ſpeak now to the ſpeculative part of his Objection; That <hi>if a Prince engage either hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Strangers, or Fugitives, or home-bred Delinquents, or others, to riſe up againſt the Senate or People, either it is lawful to defend themſelves by Arms, or not; if not, especially if they have a ſhare in the Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, then</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is the King's Power abſolute and unlimited, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Laws, or any thing below, are any ſecurity againſt his Will to the common ſafety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, in Anſwer to this, firſt it ſuppoſeth a Caſe that never can be, as a King to raiſe Forces to deſtroy his People, or any party of them; it can never be the caſe, that is, for a King to War upon his People in condition of Subjection; therefore it is ever the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple's War, reſiſting the King, in his governing Power. It may be a caſe, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> will not diſſolve, but defend themſelvs by force, and this is a making War upon the King.</p>
            <p>Now this being directly the Nature of a War betwixt King and Subjects, all the pretences to a defence are taken off, and the Queſtion comes ſimply to be, Whether for other reſpects about the Government, any party out of the King may raiſe War. This muſt of neceſſity be reſolved in the Negative, becauſe it is not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to fancy governing power with a power in the People, or any party out of the King, to reſiſt his power; for then he ſhould go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern no longer than the governed party were diſpoſed to obey, and ſo no Government at all; nor is it poſſible, in the reaſon of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, to put a power upon the governing Power, and yet that to govern: So as no Argument can be made for reſiſting, becauſe it is againſt Government it ſelf.</p>
            <p>But, ſaith Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> Then what aſſurance of Laws, all at the King's Will.</p>
            <p>Now, the preciſe conſideration upon this is, that the very Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Government, and the King's Intereſt in it, binds him to the good of it: The Law ſaith, <hi>Nulli magis tueri Rempublicam creditum eſt quàm Regi,</hi> no perſon ſo believed to intend the good of the Common-Wealth as the King, his ſole Intereſt makes it ſo; all others, as Subject<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, have private Intereſts in them, and ſo have private reſpects, which commonly conſiſts not with the publick; the King is the only publick Perſon of the Kingdom, who hath no reaſon or conſideration of his being, but as King; without that, or
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:53682:22"/>
beyond that, nothing, his whole being placed in it; the publick is his private; and this very reaſon, in Nature of Government, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Government the ſame with the King, is the full abſolute cauſe of the certainty and good of it, and is as much as is for any thing in Nature, or any Being in the World, ſince nothing can be more aſſured than Self-Intereſt for the good of it. And therefore Kingly Government is the moſt certain Government, becauſe there can be no end out of it, all contained in it; the good of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is the King's good, without any difference: Whereas in all other Forms of Government, the Perſons that govern have par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ends, as private perſons, and this is truly the Nature of it, never any reaſon can be for the abuſe of Government by a King: It may be abuſe upon the King's Government, but never out of any juſt end of it. So as it is the fouleſt miſtake that can be, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a King's Intereſt divided from the People's, and that he muſt be held in chains for the People's good and certainty of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; when as the People directly loſe all their good if the King want freedom of Will and Power to act. The People's conſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is meerly in the King's power; without that it were nothing, preſently the Government grows ſeditious and factious, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in parts, when the Regal Power cannot retain it. And hence it is, that thoſe Perſons that pretend for Liberty and Power over Kings, are cauſe of Murders, and Maſſacres, of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, if it be objected, that there are evils and abuſes under a King's Government, yet not ſo conſiderable (eſpecially here with us in <hi>England,</hi> where hardly can be any great grievance, the form of the Government being ſo equal) as to make War for them.</p>
            <p>Government hath many hard things come into it, and extream difficulties; and the evils of it are out of the People themſelves, ſtubbornly acting againſt the King, and repugning to the means of Government, and of Perſons doing wickedly, and great Ones op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing and having their ends by wicked means: Nor is it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, almoſt in any Government, to have it ſo, that the ordinary Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple can be able to find Remedy againſt the Oppreſſions of great Ones, ſuch as are wicked and turn even the Government it ſelf into the means of it, and the King is the party moſt extreamly wronged
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:53682:22"/>
in it; for all reflects upon the King, and yet it cannot be helped but in degrees, as things are ſubject to their accidents, and ſo far only the good of Government goes, and never to an abſoluteneſs. Now, the manner is, that where the univerſality meets in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> all is repreſented, and they complain, and ſupply the King's wants, and this is the great means to redreſs.</p>
            <p>And if ſome hard condition in the Government cannot be got mended at preſent, yet extreams do never long endure, but return to the nature of the Government, they cannot hold out; ſo as we ſee, all exceſſes in Government are cauſes ſtill of falling back, and reverting to its right temper, and commonly cauſes of pulling away ſomething of the former with it; as ever, all violating of the grand Charters and Liberties are cauſe of binding them up, and taking greater advantage of the King.</p>
            <p>A King can never affect to govern ill, but they may affect to have Power; for Power is not ſimply good or evil, but in the uſe of it: and to have treaſure; and the People in Parliament, not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying, Kings are inforced to break out into extraordinaries, and it cannot be helped; for it is not to be ſuppoſed a failer of the means of Government, all muſt dy and periſh before it.</p>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> in the Parliament, the 18th of his Reign, tells them, that in ten years he had not made uſe of them; and had he not bin all peace he could not have lived ſo.</p>
            <p>When the War began, the conteſt was about nothing but that they would not truſt the King, and were reſolved to bring him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them, being an inexorable party; and cruelty growing out of Religion is of all other the greateſt Cruelty: But the Laws and Rights were juſt the ſame as in all times formerly, no alteration as to the great Intereſt of Regal right and the People's Rights, which ſhews it is not alterable, that which no time had wrought upon, and all accidents had in all thoſe ages and times come into it; of ſo durable matter is the Government, as no fear ever can be in it, as to neceſſitate Arms of the People to vindicate it.</p>
            <p>The People themſelvs are the only deſtroyers of it.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, though a King may ſeem all Power, yet naturally and neceſſarily all Government involvs it ſelf into the conſent of the People, and all Power comes out of them; ſo as we are to ſee where the Intereſt of it lyes, not meerly in the King's Will, who is
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:53682:23"/>
tied to more neceſſities than any other; ſo fooliſh it is to think, that though they have the Power of governing, they have not the natural reſtraints and neceſſities of Government upon them.</p>
            <p>We are at laſt to conſider the infinite miſchſef of a Civil War, and the ſtrange danger the People run into, the greateſt and moſt devouring Gulf that is in nature, a body deſtroying its ſelf and rip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping out its own Bowels; for it is all-acted within the body it ſelf, and the People know not whether they ſhall ever return to their Government again, but live under perpetual Uſurpation and Rebellion, which utterly deſtroys a People, to fall and live under the King's deſtroyers; for Uſurpation is all wickedneſs, and all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and all force, and cannot be amended ſo long as it ſtands in reſiſtance; ſo as if poſſible, the People's Intereſt is to get out of it, and come under their Government: And it is ſo far a King of <hi>England</hi>'s cauſe, that hath no military Power in governing, as he will never inforce the People beyond Subjection, which is their beſt condition: The very end and deſign of the Government being to keep down the great Monſter of it, that threatens it; ſo as on neither ſide it can be imaginable, that Rebellion ſhould ever be the People's beſt good, remedy, or neceſſity, which is pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for it, when it is acted, being ſo wicked and unlawfull in it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Therefore we ſee it is ever, either of the People pampered with Peace, and know not what belong to War, or judge not of the good of Government, though they have it but in ſome degree good, or elſe are cheated into it by Treaſon in a party deſigning other ends.</p>
            <p>And the Vulgar, the Character of them is all folly, and evil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, as mis-judging and to be unſatisfied, ſo as never any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition makes their good under Government, but when it is utterly out of their own Power.</p>
            <p>Now the evil and deſtructive miſchief of Rebellion, as all acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of deſtroying and oppreſſing come into it, muſt needs prove the unlawfulneſs; for wherefore are things unlawful, but as they in their Natures are wicked; &amp; Rebellion being of all cauſes in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the greateſt cauſe of Wickedneſs, muſt needs be the greateſt unlawfulneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:53682:23"/>We are a little further to conſider of the difficulty of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in its ſelf, how many things naturally oppoſe to the good of it, though the common good of all the Members is placed in it, yet the moſt in their particular good or profit, would act againſt it, or ſome prejudice to it; as every unlawful acting is againſt it: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, all the dangers that come into it, and difficulty to the means of it. And ſome King's Governments, naturally as it were, though from accident, are obſtructed with difficulties and dangers, which they muſt ſtill over-come or elſe they periſh; ſo that the beſt that ever I could diſcern in it is, for a <hi>Parliament</hi> to help the King, as much as they can poſſibly to the good of it: And a King of <hi>England</hi> his neceſſity will ever bring him to meet the People in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſtill let it be noted, that reſiſtance out of a <hi>Parliament</hi> makes no difference at all; for it is rebelling ſtill againſt the governing Power, and moſt deſtructive when it ſhall pretend a lawfulneſs in another power.</p>
            <p>I ſhall come now to the King's own acting, Did he not deny his own Prerogative about Ship-money, and all other extraordinaries? Regulate the Privy-Council, and take away the Star-Chamber, High-Commiſſion-Court, diſſolve the great body of the Biſhops out of <hi>Parliament,</hi> to pleaſe the Houſe of Commons? Eſtabliſh a Triennial <hi>Parliament,</hi> paſs againſt his Judgment and Conſcience the Act for condemning and executing the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> and after grant them perpetual ſitting againſt his power of diſſolving? Did ſo much to his own preſerving, that he gave away the means of his preſervation, and wrought his own ruine by it.</p>
            <p>The like he had done before in <hi>Scotland,</hi> reſtrained his Royal power there, rewarded the very Rebels, and againſt nature, juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Acts of Emnity againſt himſelf, and declared his own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty guilty.</p>
            <p>I have ſet forth this, to ſhew the nature of Kings in this their condition, and in relation to the People, and wherein a King's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt conſiſts; that is, not to fight for his own which by peace he poſſeſſeth; and likewiſe it diſproves them about the War it ſelf, to prove the Injuſtice of it on their part, mearly affected to deſtroy the Government, and to decline the King.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:53682:24"/>To ſhew what compliers Kings are to peace, we ever ſee all Kings ſtyle their People, <hi>their good People,</hi> moſt when they fear evil from them; treat them by all poſſible means of ſatisfaction and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tearms; ſend forth Proclamations to purge any evil apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the People; awed even by the very thoughts of the People; ſuch is the nature of Government to implant fear in Kings, which is their great Governour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. the verieſt Tyrant in his nature of any man that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was, yet his Government as to the Commons was good; he acted cruelties, beyond any other King, upon particular perſons of the great Ones, whom his Jealouſy did reach to: In his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment good in general, and declined all things of breach with the People, though he ſeemed abſolutely to command them.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, There are no <hi>Princes</hi> ſo ſtout as thoſe who are moſt juſt; as Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> with her ſure ground of goodneſs to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend her, kept her <hi>Parliament</hi> and People at greateſt diſtance from encroaching upon Royal Authority. King <hi>James</hi> had innocency and worth enough in him to vindicate him ſtill; and the truth is, if the <hi>People</hi> could but weigh and penetrate into the exigencies and urgencies of State Intereſts, how hard a thing it is to do but indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently well in the Work of Government, as to the People's ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, they would not ſeek to take advantages of Kings, and hold them to extreams; and can never have any good in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it, for the misfortune of the King ever returns upon the People,</p>
            <p>It was not poſſible for the People to know their own Happineſs under the Government of former <hi>Princes;</hi> and it is a Bleſſing man never is endowed withal, to know the meaſure of his good whilſt he enjoys it; and this is the cauſe that they prize it not, but throw it away, and wilfully bring themſelvs to miſery.</p>
            <p>King <hi>James,</hi> in whoſe time the People had nothing to do but laugh, and play, and follow their own Intereſts; no great Taxes, not the half as of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> as for the time; no fear upon the Nobility, no fear or danger from the <hi>Prince</hi>'s humour, Religion perfectly <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> the King himſelf the great owner of Intereſts in the reaſon and ſcience of them; yet the People moſt ungrateful, no more ſatisfied than if they had been under a bad Government, tired out with their very peace: It is his own words to them in
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:53682:24"/>
the Parliament, 18. of his Reign, <hi>We indeed find by experience, that a number of our Subjects, are ſo pampered with peace, as they are deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of Change, though they know not what.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This happineſs continued in the ſubſtance, though not in all cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, till the people themſelves deſtroyed it, ſo as they acted their ſin and their Plague in one.</p>
            <p>We come in the next place, to that wherein he betrayes himſelf, to the utter overthrowing of his Cauſe, which I foreſaw he would do at laſt.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>If the Souldiers muſt know beforehand, that if they do pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe a Victory by their bloud, when they have all done, they muſt be Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by him whom they have conquered, and lye at his mercy, they would hardly ever have an Army to defend them; for who would do the uttermoſt that is poſſible to exaſperate him, that he knows muſt rule him when all is done?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If this be reaſon with Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> now, why not at firſt? What Faith could he have in his Covenant, which he deſtroyes by a Principle in his underſtanding? We at firſt looked upon their pretences as for King and Parliament, and all their Vows and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations, but as ſo many charms only to deſtroy the King, becauſe by other means they could not delude the people; and now he confeſſes it, concludes, and conſents to the reaſon of it; that an exaſperated King is never to be truſted again with his power over thoſe that ſubdued him; by this he deſtroyes his Covenant, his Cauſe, and the whole; onely that ſerved then, and this now.</p>
            <p>To drive this further, becauſe Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> declares himſelf ſo in it, as he can have no retreat out of it: Firſt fight their King, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due him, be Victorious upon him, make him Captive; then kill him, according to the Kings own ſenſe and ſaying when he was in that condition; That there were but few ſteps betwixt the Priſons and the Graves of Princes.</p>
            <p>Now Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> makes it his very Argument for the death of the King, and ſo involves his whole Cauſe and Party in it, has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed all difference and diſtinction, and makes the death of the King natural and conſequential to the firſt of warring upon him. We ſee here how naturally falſhoods betray themſelves out of their own Arguments.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not paſs by the inſolency and impropriety of his ſaying,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:53682:25"/>
               <hi>Conquered the King;</hi> If Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> were skilled in the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> which is out of his Element, he would know, that there can be no ſuch thing as a Conqueſt of Subjects over their King; it is deſertion, or Treaſon, not Conqueſt.</p>
            <p>If he conſult but nature, it will tell him, that that which is the proper ſtrength, exiſtency, and being of any thing, cannot be ſaid to conquer it, no more then any thing can be ſaid to conquer it ſelf; the being ceaſes to be, if the eſſentiall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> do but divide from it.<note place="margin">Cook 3. Inſt. p. 12.</note> Nay the voice and reaſon of our Laws would never call them Enemies, but Traytors; Enemies implyes a kind of equalls. He ſayes.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>It was the Judgment of the Parliament upon the diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Upon their diviſion, their dividing from the King, their Judgment was nothing, but as private perſons, or wicked enemies; all Subordination depends ſo upon its firſt Cauſe, as dividing from that, the beeing ceaſes to be.</p>
            <p>In the next, you ſhall obſerve Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> over-rule Scripture to his own ſenſe, as he hath dealt in Politicks.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>And that thoſe that did reſiſt the Higher Powers ſet over them by God, are guilty of the damnation of reſiſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This of Higher Powers here in Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> meaning, is of thoſe that raiſed the War againſt the King, that they were the Higher Powers not to be reſiſted.</p>
            <p>Now I have not met with a greater violation of Scripture then this, to make it a meer contrary to its ſelf, and deſtructive to the end it ſerves to, not only indirectly, but oppoſitely. This Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture proceeds from the Spirit of God directly for preſervation of Kings, and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> applyes it to the Kings deſtroyers, make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them the meer object of it, in the act of deſtroying the King.</p>
            <p>I have driven it thus home, to fix it upon obſervation, what a ſtrange degree of falſifying, and abuſing Scripture in it, and the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridneſs of the example, and conſequence of falſifying grounds, and rules by which truths ſhould be meaſured, and creating falſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions which are ſeeds of all wicked actions.</p>
            <p>Now to clear out this more fully and directly, paſt exception: there is not one word or ſyllable in Scripture Doctrinally, of any
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:53682:25"/>
Power or Authorities, ſince God Governed by his Prophets; but ſtill generally, the intendment is of Kings, and no other Form of Government owned in Scripture, or ever intended; that being only natural, all Power conſiſting in unity of Power; and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more the Powers are intended as part of the Kings Power; for there is no fraction in Government, ſuppoſing it a Government; ſo as all Power is ever but the Power of the chief Power.</p>
            <p>So many ſignalls upon Kings, and Guards for their fence and ſafety, becauſe if the head fail, all the parts and dependency of the people muſt needs diſſolve.</p>
            <p>And here I ſhall take up again his words; <hi>no more to be truſted with Government.</hi> A Speech of great ſcorn, and contempt upon Kings, to make them the people's Servants, and at their diſpoſe, to turn off when they will, and to deſtroy; and deriving no higher then out of the Peoples truſt, their beeing ſtill but a depending bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nothing being higher in nature then its firſt Cauſe; and upon this baſis they plant their Engine for pulling down, debaſing Kings, and caſting them into their Graves.</p>
            <p>It is good therefore to ſee the relation that Kings have.</p>
            <p>For ſo much as we ſee immediate of God in it (which is not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily in the things of the World, but limited to the choſen peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and when he appeared by his Prophets) then moſt manifeſtly the Kings, or at leaſt the firſt Kings (which ſhews the nature of it, and right of it in all) was from God, leaving out the people at all in it, to have any ſhare in it: All this legible in <hi>Saul, David, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> and in the removes of Kings by Gods ſpecial denunciation, and ſending by his Prophets: The people the Executioners in ſome caſes and circumſtances; ſo as there is no footſtep or mark from God of the Peoples title over Kings, or their making them, or give<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them their power. This in God, ſpecial, and appearing proves in all, ſhews the nature of it, for that which we ſee was done, and of God, and freely done, and at firſt when no accident had been, (ſo as it was a meer promulgation out of nature, and proper to the nature of it) muſt needs be held certain to it, and moſt reaſonable to conceive of it.</p>
            <p>Correſponding to theſe are the Texts,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>There is no Power but of God, the Powers that be are ordained of God;</hi> this referring to Kings, for the words are after, <hi>For Princes are not to be feared for good works,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:53682:26"/>
but for evill, and he is the Miniſter of God;</hi> Power, as Power, is properly of God, who is the Power.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chr. 1.9. &amp; 11.</note>
               <hi>Thou haſt made me a King over a People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That thou mayeſt Judg the People over whom I have made thee King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sam. 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. 1.</note>
               <hi>I have provided me a King;</hi> ſtill pointing out his End, and his Author.</p>
            <p>The Texts are many more, and clear it beyond all doubt, or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of man; that Kings, as Kings, are Gods Creatures, and derive not lower then from God himſelf, as immediate to him.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe this was of the Jews, a peculiar people to God, we will ſee what evidence the Scripture yields in caſe of Heathen Kings. <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> an Heathen, and Idolater, was owned by God as his Servant.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 25.9.</note>
               <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> my ſervant.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 45.1.</note>And thus ſaid the Lord to <hi>Cyrus</hi> his annointed.</p>
            <p>Which is the higheſt emblem of Soveraignty, annointing, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to <hi>Cyrus</hi> as King; that is, that he had it vertually as King.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ezr. 1.2.</note>And <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Perſia, The Lord God of Heaven hath given me the Kingdomes of the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Daniel</hi> moſt full, the Pattent of the King as extenſive to all Creatures and Powers under him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 1. ver. 37, 38.</note>
               <hi>The God of Heaven hath given thee a Kingdom, Power, and Strength, and Glory, and in all places where the Children of men dwell, the Beaſts of the field, and the Fowls of the Heaven, has he given into thy hand, and hath made thee Ruler over them all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Illuſtration of Gods dominion over all Creatures, and acting by Kings, his immediate Vice-gerents; to the end of the 5th chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Daniel,</hi> being nothing elſe then Gods clayming his Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle over Kings, as derivative from God, and accountable to him.</p>
            <p>Now all this is from the great end in nature, that Kings being to rule the people, which is Gods proper Office, and Attribute; all Power, and all Dominion, and all Providence being his, they repreſent God, and are his Image, and Effigies in Ruling and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning: and this makes their dependance to be meerly of God,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:53682:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and not accountable to any Power under God.</p>
            <p>The nature of it is ſhewed in that of <hi>Saul,</hi> as being the firſt King to the Jews, and being the inſtitutive of it, comprehends the nature of it.</p>
            <p>The perſon was meerly of Gods choice, not left to the people, nor any power left in them, much leſs over the King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In that day ſhall they cry unto the Lord,</hi> ſayes the Text; That is,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 8.18.</note> no power to be againſt the Kings Power, but an appeal only to an higher Power; that is, to God himſelf, his Author and Founder; they might complain of him that was ſet over them, but had not any Authority of their own over him.</p>
            <p>And this makes it in its nature to be the greateſt truſt in the World, becauſe there is no remedy againſt it, contrary to Mr. <hi>Baxter's</hi> ſenſe, abuſing the Term, making Truſt, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of this abſolute ſubjection of the People to Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, lyes in the nature of it, that no medium can be found betwixt power of Governing, and liberty in the people as not Governed; to be ſubject only to the good of Government, is no Government at all, or to be ſubject at all: therefore of meer force, from its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it leaves nothing in the wills of the people; ſo as no ſuch mean, or half being of it can be, by any conſtitution, proviſion, or Policy whatſoever, when it comes to Govern, all thoſe things, though part of the Government, yet come under the governing Power.</p>
            <p>Now for the Originals of Ruling Powers ordinarily amongſt men, as to the perſons ruling in ſuch a Line, and Succeſſion; we ſhall find it to be ſtill from a firſt Power, before it came to Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Power; the one introductive of the other: for Power is its matter and nature; for we ſee all Government is Power, and the Power will govern. Therefore equivocally the terms and names are uſed; ſometimes calling it the Government, and ſometimes the Power; ſo as it is the ſame, and ſignifies the ſame thing; inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perables in nature, Government and Power: no remove can be in it; for where the Power is, there the Government will go along with it.</p>
            <p>Hence it is that there is never any diſcontinuance in governing Power over the people. In the moſt confuſed tumultuous War,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:53682:27"/>
and diſtraction that ever was, yet there is power ſtill ſomewhere or other, that contains the peoples liberty, and ſubjects them; ſo as there is not one moment, or minute of time in the World, where ſociety and community of man is, that there is any <hi>vacuum</hi> of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to be over them; and although powers deveſt one another, yet the Series of governing Power is ſtill continued; and in all ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves of the Powers, yet the Power never falls, but is kept al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes up, and is in ſome ſtill, and is as inſeperable from the People, as the matter and the Form, which never are aſunder.</p>
            <p>For that which we call Power out of the People, it is not the people, but a Power acting upon the People; and in ſuch a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of it, if it become too powerful for the Government, then it becomes the Government it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Now having ſhewed thus the nature of it, it deſtroyes all thoſe imaginary Theaters that they would erect and build popular liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon, and popular right over Kings.</p>
            <p>They would fancy governing Power to be of the wills of the people, and the people the Author; ſo impoſſible an aſſertion, as I only leave it upon what I have ſtated, and how contradictory it is to nature in all conſideration of it; ſo as ſtill the people is but the ſubject matter of Government, never the Author of it, nor does Government ever come below the people in the cauſe of it, but muſt derive out of its own cauſe, which is power to be above the people, and ſo in all end and acting of it.</p>
            <p>All this is ſtill to explode that Monſtrous conceit of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples inſtituting the Government; or more Monſtrous conſequence of it, the people as the firſt cauſe of it to diſpoſe of it, and deſtroy it.</p>
            <p>It is obſervable in Government, that Laws and Liberties come afterward to the people, after power of the Government it ſelf.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Norman</hi> Conqueſt, all lay flatted ſome time under it, till afterward (as the Reporters of thoſe times tell us); that the party of the Conqueror, or their Poſterity, did revive the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: firſt the Conqueror's abſolute will ſerved them to expel, and diſpoſſeſs the Natives, and after they were glad of eſtabliſhments in Government, to aſſure their own condition, and what they had gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:53682:27"/>So as hereby we ſee Governments, the farther they go on from their beginnings, the more they take in of compoſition to their firſt ſingle Nature; ſo as ſtill the Originals of Government are moſt abſolute.</p>
            <p>Hence it is manifeſt that Power is their Fountain and firſt cauſe, as ſuch is their Natures, and the People's Freedom ſtill is under Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and when Government is moſt confuſed then is their Freedom leaſt; ſo as ſtill Power is over them, and are alwayes ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to it, let the Form of it be what it will.</p>
            <p>To conſider it in common Reaſon and Underſtanding, the King took his Being from the People's Truſt, in Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s ſenſe; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the People are to diſpoſe of him: This were for the People not to be governed, for then the Right were in the People, and the <hi>King</hi> betrayed to govern under another Authority to make it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptable. Therefore this ſuppoſeth a Monſter in nature, and it would evermore make Government deſtructive to it ſelf, for then it doth not govern; for where the end and ultimate of Power is, there the Government is.</p>
            <p>I ſhall inſert ſomething that is legal in this, pertinent to the Caſe of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> how he comes to be King. Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Coke,</hi> that was a man popular enough, in his third part of his <hi>Inſtitutes,</hi> pag. 7. ſaith, That there is no ſuch thing of the Kingly Being in <hi>England</hi> as an <hi>Inter-Regnum,</hi> nor any Act confers to the making of the King, but inſtantly by the deſcent of the Crown to the right Heir, he is King. This his, and more, there expreſt. And indeed, no worldly Power can diſpoſe, alien, or transfer the right of the Crown. King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth before his death would have ſetled the Crown upon his neareſt Kinſwoman, the Lady <hi>Jane Gray,</hi> Wife to the Lord <hi>Dudly;</hi> his Siſter <hi>Mary</hi> being of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church: and the Council and Peers ſwore to this in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and he dyed. Now, what the effect? Only to make them all Traytors, and no other right in it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Parliaments</hi> have declared for Titles, but never can make any, nor deprive Right. It is true, divers Uſurpers have had <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> Teſt for their Warrant, for thoſe have moſt need of it, but ſtill it was acted under power enforcing, and ſo it was nothing but mear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo long as the Power laſted.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:53682:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>Uſurpation doth not come into poſſeſſion without power, and it draggs <hi>Parliaments</hi> after it, and deprives all reality, but meer Hypocriſy in all that is acted or pretended to, by <hi>Parliament</hi> or Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>I have no more now to conſider of, than of the Right of <hi>Kings,</hi> having ſpoken of their Original Cauſe, Power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, this firſt is generally from the great end of it; that is, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; which, as Government, is ever good; good, as Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, though it may be an evil Government: nor can any fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the particularities ſo over-rule the common good of it, but ſtill it hath good of Government in it.</p>
            <p>But this comes not to the Queſtion of Right in the perſon which we are to inquire.</p>
            <p>Certainly it cannot be Conqueſt which is only a great Riot, and multiplying of Rapines and Man-ſlaughters; it is all Wickedneſs which is only diſtinguiſhed from common wickedneſs as it tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends all other actings of wickedneſs; and ſuch is the nature of Conqueſt by exceſs of wicedneſs, to make it ſelf above offending and puniſhment.</p>
            <p>Then it cannot be in ſubmiſſion of the People to it, being firſt conquered ſtill before they conſent; and if they partly reſiſt and gain conditions, yet it is in reſpect of the power, which is cauſe of all the following of what nature ſoever it be. And it is not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that any one can receive a Right from his doing wrong.</p>
            <p>Some ſuppoſe upon the future ſettlement and equability of the Government eſtabliſhed Title may reſult, yet ſtill all this is after the power, and cannot imply in any kind a not Being of it, being firſt ſuppoſed abſolute, at leaſt not their condition to reſiſt it.</p>
            <p>Beſides, in the Caſe of a former Right, the Peoples conſent can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not evacuate a right in the former <hi>Prince</hi> outed, or his poſterity.</p>
            <p>Now that it appears directly, that none of theſe things make right, or are of any force to it, it is cleared by this; that if the outed <hi>Prince</hi> can recover and regain Power, theſe things vaniſh as unlawful, and as wicked conſentings and compliance; and ſo long as the old Right can poſſibly retain its ſelf in memory, add but pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to it, and it is ever unqueſtionable.</p>
            <p>One inſtance with us in <hi>England</hi> of ſixty years diſcontinuance; yet when it recovered power to act, all the Uſurpation went for
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:53682:28"/>
nothing, and the old came in as Right, not as Conqueſt.</p>
            <p>Where yet ſhall we find it? Nothing but the Old extinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by long continuance of the latter, and that becoming natural, and conſent goes with Nature; ſo hard it is to the Titles of <hi>Princes</hi> and ſo precious to the People to retain them, and ſo dangerous to loſe them; And all the Intervals filled, and taken up with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty of Government, and all the accidents that attend want of Title.</p>
            <p>Therefore, ſince only time, and long time, makes unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Right to Princes, it is of all Rights or Titles the hardeſt to be attained to, and muſt be moſt abſolute, ſince nothing but Uſer can give in its Authority; therefore it is moſt unqueſtionable, venerable, unchangable, independent of any other Cauſe, and ſo under no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther power, and never falls but with the ruine of the People.</p>
            <p>And this is a high perfection of Kingly Government, ſince no other Form of Government can have this precious thing, Title in it; that is, Right in the Perſon, which is the Cement of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and half the means of it; and conſent goes along with it whereby all the People act ſubordinately, and this makes it eaſy and without force, becauſe of this tacite conſent of the People to it; for all operation of the Soul is but conſent, conſent is the geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us of the Government by which it acts, and all the People, and all common Intereſt doth center in the Right of it, and find their reſt.</p>
            <p>And now I have done with the Argument.</p>
            <p>I have only ſomething of Obſervation from the natural effects of Rebellion, and deſtroying rightful Government, as we ſee it in ours: Now, the Work is done, and all in the Power of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers; What comes of it? Two very natural and great effects; the one is Wickedneſs, all manner of wickedneſs, impieties, falſe Religions, Cruelty of manners and actings, multiplicity of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants; having deſtroyed the great Tyrant-Government under a King, as they called it, all perſons that get Power, act as Tyrants: Multitude of Tyrants out of the People themſelves, acting wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in all parts, Cities, and Towns, where moſt Intereſt of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple lies; ſtrange Principles in profeſſion and opinion, and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing rancks and degrees of perſons, and of Kings, and Supreams, and bringing all into a contempt and baſeneſs, againſt order of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:53682:29"/>
and nature of Government, which conſiſts in difference, and degrees, and ſubordination. To follow this ſubject of our preſent condition, what a Monſter <hi>England</hi> is become, no ſuch Copy of it in the World? It muſt be all written and taken out of it ſelf; the ſtrange infinite forms of Wickedneſs both in Faith and manners, baſe horrible Conceptions, monſtrous Notions; all hatched, and have their production from the putrified matter of ſtanding in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Rebellion, and looſed from the rightful governing Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and running looſe into parties and into their own ſenſe, having caſt off the right Power, which keeps to Order and Unity, all Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Unity being the effect of Government; and the Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrouſneſs and Infiniteneſs that enters in the vacancy or deficiency of it; for Errors in their nature are infinite, whereas all true Beings have but their natural proportions and definitions.</p>
            <p>The other is unſettledneſs, which is the Curſe of Uſurpation, and of deſtroying rightful Government, that it cannot reſolve it ſelf into any thing of certainty or Being to the People, under the power of it: As we ſee theſe perſons, to perpetuate their Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, can make nothing of it.</p>
            <p>The King's Right, and the wrong they do, doth ſhine out of darkneſs it ſelf, out of that rubbiſh of confuſion and deſtruction they would bury it under: We ſee they can make nothing of all the Power, having the whole, it being the King's Power and the King's Right; they are confounded with it, do but toſs and tumble this Power over and over, it can no where ſettle to make a Government, but monſtrous violence grows out of it; and this is all they can cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate from it, which doth admirably confirm the King's right, and that only in that doth conſiſt the People's Intereſt; and what a ſtrange ſpirit and principle is in it, that though troden down, and debaſed, reviled, ſcandalized, and kept out, yet it riſeth againſt all Power, not in nature left, or poſſible to make a ſettlement, or Juſtice, or Safety, to the People without it; the People undone by the uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping it; ſo dangerous is a King's Right when deveſted and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placed, and ſo precious to preſerve in its true place.</p>
            <p>My laſt I will conclude withal, which may reflect upon the whole, is, that I conceive the beſt way of calling <hi>Parliaments</hi> is frequently, and never by neceſſity; for when a King hath moſt need, it proves moſt dangerous; therefore it is never to be uſed as
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:53682:29"/>
the laſt remedy. Kings ought to have ſomething in reſerve to help them off that again if it grow averſe, and incline to danger. And it was the total ruine of the King, that he was ſo much a loſer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he came to play this Game: When all was diſtempered and diſordered round about, the out-Nations up in Arms, and the home-People poyſoned, diſcontented, then he calls a <hi>Parliament,</hi> when no thing totally, and mainly, could have deſtroyed him but that; for every grievance, and every miſery, and every diſtreſs of the King's ſerved them for matter againſt the King; and ſo turned the cauſe of putting himſelf upon them for help, to be the means of their depreſſing him, and deſtroying him. It is like that our Saviour ſaith, putting a new piece of Cloth into an old Garment, it makes the rent worſe; ſo all the parts ſo fear, and unſound, as nothing to bear the ſearching, ſevere remedy of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and apt to grow wicked with their Power.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
